<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-12-11</actionDate>
          <text>Placed on the Union Calendar, Calendar No. 494.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Trade Secrets Protection Act of 2014</latestTitle>
        <number>5233</number>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:29:52Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Judiciary Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2014-04-29T20:08:01Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <systemCode>ssju00</systemCode>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Coons, Christopher A. [D-DE]</fullName>
        <middleName>A.</middleName>
        <bioguideId>C001088</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1984</lisID>
          <bioguideId>C001088</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8297</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <lastName>Coons</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>DE</state>
        <firstName>Christopher</firstName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Crime and Law Enforcement</name>
    </policyArea>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2014-04-29</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on the Judiciary.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <middleName>GRANT</middleName>
        <state>UT</state>
        <firstName>ORRIN</firstName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>H000338</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Hatch, Orrin G. [R-UT]</fullName>
        <lastName>HATCH</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-04-29</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1351</lisID>
          <gpoId>8314</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>H000338</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <billNumber>2267</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Defend Trade Secrets Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to modify chapter 90 of title 18, United States Code, to provide Federal jurisdiction for theft of trade secrets.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Defend Trade Secrets Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <createDate>2014-04-30T07:25:27Z</createDate>
    <notes />
    <title>Defend Trade Secrets Act of 2014</title>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Business ethics</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Business records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Crimes against property</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Evidence and witnesses</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Fraud offenses and financial crimes</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Jurisdiction and venue</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Product development and innovation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Trade secrets and economic espionage</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Crime and Law Enforcement</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <updateDate>2014-04-29T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Defend Trade Secrets Act of 2014 - Amends the federal criminal code to authorize an owner of a trade secret who is aggrieved by an act of economic espionage, theft of a trade secret, or misappropriation of a trade secret that is related to a product or service used in, or intended for use in, interstate or foreign commerce to bring a civil action under this Act (current law authorizes the Attorney General to bring a civil action to obtain injunctive relief against any violation of provisions regarding the protection of trade secrets).</p> <p>Authorizes the court, based on an affidavit or verified complaint satisfying the requirements of this Act, upon ex parte application and if the court finds that issuing the order is necessary to prevent irreparable harm, to issue appropriate orders: (1) providing for the preservation of evidence in the civil action, including by making a copy of an electronic storage medium that contains the trade secret; (2) granting an injunction to prevent any actual or threatened violation, (3) requiring affirmative actions to be taken to protect a trade secret; or (4) providing for the seizure of any property used to commit or facilitate the commission of an alleged violation, except that such an order may not provide for the seizure of any property that is merely incidental to the alleged violation unless necessary to preserve evidence or shall provide for the seizure of any property in a manner that does not interrupt normal and legitimate business operations unrelated to the trade secret.</p> <p>Makes applicable to such ex parte applications and seizure orders specified requirements of the Trademark Act of 1946 regarding ex parte applications and seizure orders in civil actions arising out of the use of counterfeit marks in connection with the sale, offering for sale, or distribution of goods or services. </p> <p>Authorizes a court in a civil action brought under this Act to: (1) grant an injunction to prevent any violation, to require affirmative actions to be taken to protect a trade secret, and to condition future use upon payment of a reasonable royalty for no longer than the period use could have been prohibited; (2) award damages for actual loss, damages for unjust enrichment, and (in lieu of damages measured by any other methods) damages caused by misappropriation measured by imposition of liability for a reasonable royalty for the unauthorized disclosure or use of a trade secret; (3) award exemplary treble damages if the trade secret is willfully or maliciously misappropriated; and (4) award reasonable attorney's fees to the prevailing party if a claim of misappropriation is made in bad faith, a motion to terminate an injunction is made or opposed in bad faith, or a trade secret is willfully and maliciously misappropriated.</p> <p>Establishes a five-year limitations period, beginning when the misappropriation is discovered or should have been discovered.</p>]]></text>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDate>2014-04-29</actionDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-07-30T21:19:00Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <introducedDate>2014-04-29</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <committeeReports />
    <actions>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-04-29</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Judiciary Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssju00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on the Judiciary.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <actionDate>2014-04-29</actionDate>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <links />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <recordedVotes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

