<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Terminating the Expansion of Too-Big-To-Fail Act of 2013</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>A bill to amend the Financial Stability Act of 2010 to repeal certain designation authority of the Financial Stability Oversight Council, to repeal the Payment, Clearing, and Settlement Supervision Act of 2010, and for other purposes.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Terminating the Expansion of Too-Big-To-Fail Act of 2013</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <name>Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee</name>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>ssbk00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-01-23T19:33:10Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Terminating the Expansion of Too-Big-To-Fail Act of 2013 - Amends the Financial Stability Act of 2010, title I of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (Dodd-Frank), the Federal Deposit Insurance Act, and the Federal Reserve Act to eliminate all supervision by the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (Board) of domestic and foreign nonbank financial companies, including new or heightened standards and safeguards and minimum leverage capital requirements.</p> <p>Eliminates the duty of the Financial Stability Oversight Council to identify systemically important financial market utilities and payment, clearing, and settlement activities.</p> <p>Repeals the authority of the Council, acting through the Office of Financial Research, to: (1) require the submission of periodic and other reports from any domestic or foreign nonbank financial company, or (2) request the Board to examine a U.S. nonbank financial company for the sole purpose of determining whether it should be Board-supervised.</p> <p>Repeals specified additional Board authority to supervise certain nonbank financial companies, including the prohibition against management interlocks between such companies and certain other financial companies.</p> <p>Repeals the requirement that the Board study and report to Congress on: (1) specified issues with respect to the resolution of financial companies under chapter 7 (Liquidation) or 11 (Reorganization) of the Bankruptcy Code, and (2) international coordination relating to the resolution of systemic financial companies under the U.S. Bankruptcy Code and applicable foreign law.</p> <p>Repeals the authority of the Council to recommend to the Board: (1) prudential standards and reporting and disclosure requirements for Board-supervised nonbank financial companies, and (2) any requirement that each nonbank financial company report periodically the company's credit exposure as well as its plan for rapid and orderly resolution in the event of material financial distress or failure.</p> <p>Repeals the requirement that the Council study the feasibility, benefits, costs, and structure of a contingent capital requirement for Board-supervised nonbank financial companies.</p> <p>Eliminates reporting requirements for such companies.</p> <p>Repeals the Payment, Clearing, and Settlement Supervision Act of 2010 (title VIII of Dodd-Frank).</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-01-23T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-02-04T16:48:35Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-01-23</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <recordedVotes />
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <middleName />
        <firstName>David</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1609</lisID>
          <gpoId>8267</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>V000127</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Vitter</lastName>
        <fullName>Sen. Vitter, David [R-LA]</fullName>
        <party>R</party>
        <byRequestType />
        <bioguideId>V000127</bioguideId>
        <state>LA</state>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Finance and Financial Sector</name>
    </policyArea>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <billType>S</billType>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:20:04Z</updateDate>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <notes />
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2013-01-23</actionDate>
      <links />
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <createDate>2013-01-24T07:00:56Z</createDate>
    <cosponsors />
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-01-23</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssbk00</systemCode>
          <name>Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2013-01-23</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <title>Terminating the Expansion of Too-Big-To-Fail Act of 2013</title>
    <relatedBills />
    <billNumber>100</billNumber>
    <laws />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Finance and Financial Sector</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Banking and financial institutions regulation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Bankruptcy</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Commodities markets</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Commodity Futures Trading Commission</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Federal Reserve System</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Financial services and investments</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Insurance industry and regulation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Securities</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC)</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <introducedDate>2013-01-23</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <committeeReports />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

