<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2014-07-17</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on the Judiciary.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <committeeReports />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>ssju00</systemCode>
          <subcommittees />
          <type>Standing</type>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <name>Judiciary Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-07-17T22:01:35Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <laws />
    <createDate>2014-07-18T04:57:56Z</createDate>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-07-17</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssju00</systemCode>
          <name>Judiciary Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on the Judiciary.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2014-07-17</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <recordedVotes />
    <amendments />
    <introducedDate>2014-07-17</introducedDate>
    <billNumber>2632</billNumber>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Immigration</name>
    </policyArea>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Amends the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 to declare that any unaccompanied alien child (UAC) who has not been a victim of a severe form of trafficking in persons or does not have a credible fear of persecution on returning to his or her country of nationality (or of last habitual residence) shall be: (1) placed in removal proceedings, (2) eligible for voluntary departure at no cost to the child, and (3) provided with access to counsel. (Currently such expedited removal requirements apply only to unaccompanied children from countries contiguous to the United States.) </p> <p>Directs the Secretary of State to negotiate repatriation agreements between the United States and countries from which large numbers of UACs are unlawfully entering the United States. (Currently such agreements are to be negotiated between the United States and countries contiguous to the United States.)</p> <p>Requires that a UAC be placed on a return flight to his or her country of nationality (or of last habitual residence) within 72 hours of screening barring cost, feasibility, and any relevant repatriation agreements. </p> <p>Provides for expedited removal of a UAC who is a member of, or affiliated with, a criminal street gang.</p> <p>Requires mandatory Department of Homeland Security (DHS) detention of a UAC apprehended by U.S. Border Patrol or U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) until the child: (1) voluntarily departs or is removed from the United States, or (2) is admitted as a refugee or asylee.</p> <p>Amends the Immigration and Nationality Act to require an immigration judge to: (1) conduct a proceeding to inspect and determine the status of a UAC who is an applicant for U.S. admission not later than 7 days after the child's screening, and (2) determine within 72 hours of the proceeding's conclusion whether a UAC is admissible (or eligible for relief from removal) or should be removed (unless the alien claims asylum or a substantial fear of persecution).</p> <p>States that: (1) if a UAC intends to make a claim of asylum or substantial fear of persecution the child shall be referred to an asylum officer who shall determine in an interview whether there is a substantial fear of persecution, and (2) if there is no substantiated fear of persecution the UAC shall be ordered removed without further hearing or review.</p> <p>Revises the definition of &quot;refugee.&quot;</p> <p>Requires DHS detention of an alien seeking asylum until the alien is removed or granted asylum.</p> <p>Extends the bar on U.S. reentry to 10 years for previously removed aliens and for certain aliens who were illegally in the United States but voluntarily departed.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary of DHS to report to Congress annually detailing apprehended illegal aliens, voluntary departures, removals, and grants of refugee or asylee status.</p>]]></text>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-09-03T21:09:06Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <updateDate>2014-07-17T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDate>2014-07-17</actionDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative remedies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Border security and unlawful immigration</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Child safety and welfare</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Justice</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Detention of persons</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Due process and equal protection</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Immigration status and procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Juvenile crime and gang violence</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Refugees, asylum, displaced persons</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Immigration</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <title>A bill to provide for the expedited processing of unaccompanied alien children illegally entering the United States, and for other purposes.</title>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:31:34Z</updateDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <title>A bill to provide for the expedited processing of unaccompanied alien children illegally entering the United States, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>A bill to provide for the expedited processing of unaccompanied alien children illegally entering the United States, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <state>LA</state>
        <firstName>David</firstName>
        <byRequestType />
        <bioguideId>V000127</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Vitter, David [R-LA]</fullName>
        <lastName>Vitter</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <middleName />
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>V000127</bioguideId>
          <lisID>1609</lisID>
          <gpoId>8267</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <number>5163</number>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>To provide for the expedited processing of unaccompanied alien children illegally entering the United States, and for other purposes.</latestTitle>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Immigration and Border Security.</text>
          <actionDate>2014-09-02</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <cosponsors />
    <billType>S</billType>
    <notes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

