<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-06-26</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2014-06-26</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <introducedDate>2014-06-26</introducedDate>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:31:16Z</updateDate>
    <createDate>2014-06-27T05:08:00Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <subcommittees />
          <type>Standing</type>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-06-26T21:32:09Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <cosponsors />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <title>Motor Vehicle Safety Act of 2014</title>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>Motor Vehicle Safety Act of 2014</title>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>A bill to provide greater transparency, accountability, and safety authority to the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, and for other purposes.</title>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>Motor Vehicle Safety Act of 2014</title>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <committeeReports />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Motor Vehicle Safety Act of 2014 - Revises early warning reporting requirements for manufacturers of motor vehicles regarding possible defects of motor vehicles and motor vehicle equipment. </p> <p>Requires the Secretary of Transportation (DOT) to issue regulations establishing categories of information that must be made available to the public. Requires the public disclosure of possible defects of motor vehicles or related equipment reported to the Secretary by motor vehicle manufacturers (Early Warning data).</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to: (1) take specified actions to improve public accessibility to information on National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA) vehicle safety databases, and (2) promulgate rules requiring the senior senior official for safety for a corporation to be responsible for requests for information in NHTSA safety or compliance investigations.</p> <p>Requires the Department of Transportation (DOT) Office of the Inspector General to study NHTSA use of Early Warning data. </p> <p>Prohibits certain vehicle safety officials, for the two-year period after termination of NHTSA employment, from knowingly making any communication to or appearance before NHTSA on behalf of a manufacturer subject to NHTSA regulation in connection with any matter involving vehicle safety on which such person seeks official action by a NHTSA officer or employee. </p> <p>Prohibits a motor vehicle manufacturer or any other person subject to federal motor vehicle safety regulation from employing NHTSA employees for the two-year period following the employee's termination of employment with NHTSA. Prescribes civil penalties for violations of such prohibition.</p> <p>Establishes the Vehicle Safety Fund to meet U.S. obligations in carrying out NHTSA vehicle safety programs. Requires the Secretary to assess and collect, for deposit in the Fund, a vehicle safety user fee from the manufacturer for each motor vehicle certified compliant with applicable motor vehicle safety standards. </p> <p>Increases civil penalties for persons who violate federal motor vehicle safety requirements. Eliminates the maximum civil penalty for a related series of daily violations.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary to: (1) notify manufacturers of motor vehicles or replacement equipment whose defect or noncompliance with federal motor vehicle safety standards presents an imminent hazard of serious injury or death; and (2) order such manufacturers to notify immediately the owners, purchasers, and dealers of the vehicle or equipment of such hazard, and to remedy the defect or noncompliance.</p> <p>Prohibits a dealer from selling or leasing a used passenger motor vehicle unless: (1) the dealer clearly and conspicuously notifies the purchaser or lessee in writing of any unremedied defects or noncompliance with federal motor vehicle safety standards, and (2) the purchaser or lessee acknowledges in writing receipt of such notification.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2014-06-26T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-09-25T18:27:05Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2014-06-26</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <notes />
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <recordedVotes />
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <number>4364</number>
        <type>HR</type>
        <latestTitle>Motor Vehicle Safety Act of 2014</latestTitle>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-04-04</actionDate>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Commerce, Manufacturing, and Trade.</text>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative remedies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Advanced technology and technological innovations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Business ethics</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Business records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Consumer affairs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Transportation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government ethics and transparency, public corruption</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government trust funds</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Motor vehicles</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Product safety and quality</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation programs funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation safety and security</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>User charges and fees</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <laws />
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
      <actionDate>2014-06-26</actionDate>
    </latestAction>
    <billNumber>2559</billNumber>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
    </policyArea>
    <amendments />
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <firstName>JAY</firstName>
        <party>D</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Rockefeller, John D., IV [D-WV]</fullName>
        <bioguideId>R000361</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1424</lisID>
          <gpoId>8273</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>R000361</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>ROCKEFELLER</lastName>
        <middleName />
        <state>WV</state>
        <byRequestType />
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <calendarNumbers />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

