<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Geothermal Exploration and Technology Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>A bill to promote the mapping and development of United States geothermal resources by establishing a direct loan program for high risk geothermal exploration wells, to amend the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007 to improve geothermal energy technology and demonstrate the use of geothermal energy in large scale thermal applications, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Geothermal Exploration and Technology Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <subcommittees />
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2013-02-14T22:37:54Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-03-09T17:05:42Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Geothermal Exploration and Technology Act of 2013 - Requires the Secretary of Energy (DOE) to: (1)&nbsp;establish a direct loan program for high risk geothermal exploration wells, and (2) give preference to loans to carry out projects that are likely to lead to successful new geothermal development leading to electricity production. Requires data from exploratory wells to be provided to the DOE Secretary (Secretary) and the Secretary of the Interior for use in mapping national geothermal resources and other uses, including subsurface geologic data, metadata, borehole temperature data, and inclusion in DOE's National Geothermal Data System. Requires the Secretary to determine the number of wells for each selected geothermal project for which a loan may be made. Requires: (1) a recipient to commence repayment of the loan beginning on the earlier of four years after the loan is made or when the geothermal facility enters into commercial production, and (2) loans for successful wells to be repaid by the developer within 10 years.</p> <p>Establishes the Geothermal Investment Fund to carry out such program. Requires amounts repaid on loans to be deposited in such Fund.<br /></p> <p>Amends the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007 to require: the Assistant Secretary for Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy to: (1) establish a program of research, development, demonstration, and commercial application for geothermal heat pumps and the direct use of geothermal energy; (2) identify and mitigate potential environmental impacts; (3) make grants to promote the development of geothermal heat pumps and the direct use of geothermal energy; (4) give priority to proposals that apply to large buildings, commercial districts, and residential communities; and (5) conduct a national solicitation for grant applications.</p> <p>Amends the Geothermal Steam Act of 1970 to provide that land under an oil and gas lease issued pursuant to the Mineral Leasing Act or the Mineral Leasing Act for Acquired Lands that is subject to an approved application for a permit to drill and from which oil and gas production is occurring may be available for leasing for geothermal drilling in order to provide for the coproduction of geothermal energy with oil and gas, if&nbsp;the lease would serve&nbsp;the public interest.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-02-14T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-02-14</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <recordedVotes />
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <middleName />
        <firstName>Jon</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1829</lisID>
          <gpoId>8258</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>T000464</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Tester</lastName>
        <fullName>Sen. Tester, Jon [D-MT]</fullName>
        <party>D</party>
        <byRequestType />
        <bioguideId>T000464</bioguideId>
        <state>MT</state>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Energy</name>
    </policyArea>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <billType>S</billType>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:21:05Z</updateDate>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <notes />
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2013-02-14</actionDate>
      <links />
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <createDate>2013-02-15T07:00:53Z</createDate>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Begich, Mark [D-AK]</fullName>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>B001265</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1898</lisID>
          <bioguideId>B001265</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8301</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-02-14</sponsorshipDate>
        <lastName>Begich</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>AK</state>
        <firstName>Mark</firstName>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-02-14</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-02-14</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <title>Geothermal Exploration and Technology Act of 2013</title>
    <relatedBills />
    <billNumber>362</billNumber>
    <laws />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Energy</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Alternative and renewable resources</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Energy efficiency and conservation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Energy research</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government lending and loan guarantees</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government trust funds</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Land use and conservation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Lighting and heating</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Oil and gas</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Research and development</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <introducedDate>2013-02-14</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <committeeReports />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

