<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <cosponsors />
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Education</name>
    </policyArea>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:32:02Z</updateDate>
    <recordedVotes />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <createDate>2014-08-01T10:29:47Z</createDate>
    <committeeReports />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Increasing Student Achievement by Increasing Student Support Act - Directs the Secretary of Education to award competitive, renewable, five-year grants to partnerships between low-income local educational agencies (LEAs) and schools offering graduate programs in school counseling, social work, or psychology to increase the number of program graduates employed by low-income LEAs.</p> <p>Defines &quot;low-income LEAs&quot; as those that: (1) serve students at least 20% of whom are from families with incomes below the federal poverty level; and (2) have no more than 1 school counselor for every 275 students, 1 school psychologist for every 770 students, and 1 school social worker for every 440 students.</p> <p>Allows the use of grant funds to: </p> <ul> <li> provide program graduate students with field training at partnership LEA schools; </li> <li> contribute to program graduates' salaries at such schools for up to three years after they graduate; </li> <li> increase the number of school counselors, social workers, and psychologists per student, and from underrepresented backgrounds, in such schools; </li> <li> enhance the capacity of partnership graduate schools to train such professionals; </li> <li> develop course work designed to facilitate such graduates' service to low-income LEAs and at-risk students; and </li> <li> provide tuition credits to such graduate students and student loan forgiveness to program graduates employed as school counselors, social workers, or psychologists by low-income LEAs for at least five consecutive years.</li> </ul> <p>Directs the Secretary to establish a program providing student loan forgiveness to non-participants in this Act's grant program who have been employed for at least five consecutive years as school counselors, social workers, or psychologists by low-income LEAs.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary to identify a formula for future use in designating regions as eligible for benefit programs due to their having a shortage of such school personnel.</p>]]></text>
          <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <updateDate>2014-07-31T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-10-06T18:27:43Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Child health</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Education of the disadvantaged</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Education programs funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Elementary and secondary education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Higher education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Mental health</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Social work, volunteer service, charitable organizations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Student aid and college costs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Teaching, teachers, curricula</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Wages and earnings</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Education</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <notes />
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <relatedBills />
    <title>Increasing Student Achievement by Increasing Student Support Act</title>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <laws />
    <billNumber>2753</billNumber>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <introducedDate>2014-07-31</introducedDate>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2014-07-31T20:50:04Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <state>MT</state>
        <bioguideId>T000464</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1829</lisID>
          <bioguideId>T000464</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8258</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>D</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Tester, Jon [D-MT]</fullName>
        <firstName>Jon</firstName>
        <lastName>Tester</lastName>
        <middleName />
        <byRequestType />
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <title>Increasing Student Achievement by Increasing Student Support Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>A bill to increase the recruitment and retention of school counselors, school social workers, and school psychologists by low-income local educational agencies.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Increasing Student Achievement by Increasing Student Support Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <amendments />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

