<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:19:57Z</updateDate>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Secure Chemical Facilities Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to enhance the security of chemical facilities and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Secure Chemical Facilities Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <lastName>LAUTENBERG</lastName>
        <firstName>FRANK</firstName>
        <bioguideId>L000123</bioguideId>
        <middleName>R.</middleName>
        <state>NJ</state>
        <fullName>Sen. Lautenberg, Frank R. [D-NJ]</fullName>
        <party>D</party>
        <byRequestType />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1381</lisID>
          <bioguideId>L000123</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8245</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <introducedDate>2013-01-23</introducedDate>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-01-31T19:48:05Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Secure Chemical Facilities Act - Amends the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to set forth provisions for the regulation of security practices at chemical facilities. </p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary of Homeland Security to designate: (1) any chemical substance as a substance of concern and establish and adjust the threshold quantity for each such substance after considering the potential extent of death, injury, and serious adverse effects that could result from a chemical facility terrorist incident; and (2) a chemical facility as a covered chemical facility if the Secretary determines such facility is a sufficient security risk (e.g., a likely target of a chemical facility terrorist incident and close to large population centers). </p> <p>Directs the Secretary to: (1) maintain a list of covered chemical facilities that are of sufficient security risk; (2) assign each covered facility to one of four risk-based tiers; (3) establish standards and procedures for security vulnerability assessments and site security plans; (4) require each facility owner or operator to submit and, once approved, to implement such an assessment and plan; and (5) establish risk-based chemical security performance standards for site security plans. </p> <p>Permits the Secretary, under specified circumstances, to: (1) accept an alternate security program submitted by the owner or operator of the facility, (2) conduct facility security inspections, and (3) obtain access to and copy records necessary for reviewing or analyzing a security vulnerability assessment or site security plan. </p> <p>Requires the Secretary to: (1) share threat information with owners, operators, or security officers of a covered chemical facility and with relevant state and local government authorities in a timely manner; and (2) disapprove a security vulnerability assessment or site security plan if the Secretary determines that such assessment or security plan does not comply with the requirements of this Act. Establishes whistleblower protections for employees of a covered chemical facility who report safety violations.</p> <p>Establishes in the Department of Homeland Security (DHS) an Office of Chemical Facility Security. </p> <p>Authorizes civil actions by individuals alleging violations of this Act.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to: (1) establish a notification system to report, via telephonic and Internet-based means, a suspected security deficiency or suspected noncompliance with the requirements of this Act; and (2) assess the emergency response resources that would be required to feasibly respond to a worst-case chemical facility terrorist incident. </p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-01-23T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-01-23</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Emergency Management</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative remedies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Homeland Security</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Emergency planning and evacuation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Employment discrimination and employee rights</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Evidence and witnesses</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Executive agency funding and structure</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Fires</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Hazardous wastes and toxic substances</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Higher education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Homeland security</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Industrial facilities</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Performance measurement</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Personnel records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Solid waste and recycling</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Terrorism</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water quality</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water use and supply</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cosponsors />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-01-23</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2013-01-23</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <title>Secure Chemical Facilities Act</title>
    <createDate>2013-01-24T07:00:55Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2013-01-23</actionDate>
      <links />
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Emergency Management</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billNumber>68</billNumber>
    <laws />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <relatedBills />
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-01-23T15:55:16Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <committeeReports />
    <notes />
    <amendments />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

