<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2014-06-03</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Foreign Relations.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <committeeReports />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>ssfr00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-06-03T20:44:19Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Foreign Relations Committee</name>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <laws />
    <createDate>2014-06-04T07:20:41Z</createDate>
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-06-03</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssfr00</systemCode>
          <name>Foreign Relations Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Foreign Relations.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-06-03</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <recordedVotes />
    <amendments />
    <introducedDate>2014-06-03</introducedDate>
    <billNumber>2421</billNumber>
    <policyArea>
      <name>International Affairs</name>
    </policyArea>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-06-30T17:01:10Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <updateDate>2014-06-03T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <actionDate>2014-06-03</actionDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Food for Peace Reform Act of 2014 - Establishes the Food for Peace program in the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) under the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961. (Repeals authority for the current program under title II of the Food for Peace Act, including certain U.S. commodity purchase, U.S. cargo, and monetization requirements.)</p> <p>Authorizes USAID to provide emergency and nonemergency foreign assistance, including through the provision of U.S. commodities or local or regional procurement.</p> <p>Authorizes nonemergency assistance to combat malnutrition and hunger, mitigate food crises, and promote resilient food security.</p> <p>Sets forth minimum funding levels for nonemergency assistance.</p> <p>Establishes the Food Aid Consultative Group, which shall: </p> <ul> <li>test options for improved product packaging and storage; </li> <li> reform commodity acquisition and supply chain management; </li> <li>increase private sector development in food aid products, packaging, and delivery; </li> <li>provide guidance on how best to use food aid commodities, including guidance on ensuring that the products reach their intended recipients; and </li> <li> strengthen commodity quality monitoring.</li> </ul> <p>Requires USAID to: </p> <ul> <li>assess the types and quality of agricultural commodities and products donated for food aid; </li> <li>adjust products to cost-effectively meet nutrient needs of target populations; </li> <li> test prototypes; </li> <li> adopt new, or improve existing, specifications for micronutrient fortified food aid products;</li> <li> develop program guidance for matching products to nutrient purposes; and </li> <li> evaluate performance and cost-effectiveness of food products and programs for vulnerable groups, such as pregnant mothers and young children. </li> </ul> <p>Authorizes ocean transportation of agricultural commodities to be procured through full and open competitive procedures.</p> <p>Requires USAID to avoid displacing sales of U.S. agricultural commodities. </p> <p>Prohibits Program assistance from being made available unless USAID determines that the provision of the agricultural commodity in the recipient country would not: (1) result in substantial interference with the domestic production or marketing of agricultural commodities in the country, or (2) have a disruptive impact on the agricultural producers or the local economy of the country.</p> <p> Expresses the sense of Congress that the U.S. Merchant Marine: (1) is a critical component of the nation's military and economic security; and (2) consists of a fleet of private, U.S.-registered merchant ships that provides domestic and international transportation for passengers and cargo.</p>]]></text>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Executive agency funding and structure</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Food assistance and relief</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Foreign aid and international relief</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Marine and inland water transportation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>International Affairs</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <title>Food for Peace Reform Act of 2014</title>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:30:40Z</updateDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Food for Peace Reform Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to amend the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (22 U.S.C. 2151 et seq.) to reform the Food for Peace Program, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Food for Peace Reform Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <state>TN</state>
        <firstName>Bob</firstName>
        <byRequestType />
        <bioguideId>C001071</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Corker, Bob [R-TN]</fullName>
        <lastName>Corker</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <middleName />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1825</lisID>
          <bioguideId>C001071</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8294</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <relatedBills />
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Coons, Christopher A. [D-DE]</fullName>
        <middleName>A.</middleName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>C001088</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1984</lisID>
          <bioguideId>C001088</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8297</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-06-03</sponsorshipDate>
        <lastName>Coons</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>DE</state>
        <firstName>Christopher</firstName>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <notes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

