<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <relatedBills />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:32:09Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2014-09-10T15:33:59Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Blumenthal, Richard [D-CT]</fullName>
        <middleName />
        <bioguideId>B001277</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>B001277</bioguideId>
          <lisID>2076</lisID>
          <gpoId>8332</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <lastName>Blumenthal</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>CT</state>
        <firstName>Richard</firstName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
    </policyArea>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2014-09-10</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <middleName>E.</middleName>
        <firstName>CHARLES</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>S000148</bioguideId>
          <lisID>1036</lisID>
          <gpoId>8279</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <lastName>SCHUMER</lastName>
        <fullName>Sen. Schumer, Charles E. [D-NY]</fullName>
        <party>D</party>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>S000148</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-09-10</sponsorshipDate>
        <state>NY</state>
      </item>
      <item>
        <middleName>E.</middleName>
        <firstName>Kirsten</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>G000555</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8336</gpoId>
          <lisID>1866</lisID>
        </identifiers>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <lastName>Gillibrand</lastName>
        <fullName>Sen. Gillibrand, Kirsten E. [D-NY]</fullName>
        <party>D</party>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>G000555</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-09-10</sponsorshipDate>
        <state>NY</state>
      </item>
      <item>
        <middleName />
        <firstName>Christopher</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1837</lisID>
          <bioguideId>M001169</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>7870</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <lastName>Murphy</lastName>
        <fullName>Sen. Murphy, Christopher S. [D-CT]</fullName>
        <party>D</party>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>M001169</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-09-10</sponsorshipDate>
        <state>CT</state>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <billNumber>2784</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Rail Safety Improvement Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>A bill to direct the Secretary of Transportation to carry out activities to improve rail safety, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Rail Safety Improvement Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <createDate>2014-09-11T05:01:18Z</createDate>
    <notes />
    <title>Rail Safety Improvement Act of 2014</title>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Accidents</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Commuting</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Connecticut</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Transportation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Emergency planning and evacuation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Fires</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Hazardous wastes and toxic substances</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>New Jersey</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>New York City</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>New York State</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Oil and gas</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Railroads</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Roads and highways</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Technology assessment</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Telephone and wireless communication</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation employees</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation programs funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation safety and security</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Worker safety and health</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDate>2014-09-10</actionDate>
          <updateDate>2014-09-10T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2015-01-09T21:56:48Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Rail Safety Improvement Act of 2014 - Reauthorizes appropriations to the Secretary of Transportation (DOT) for FY2015-FY2020 to carry out rail safety activities for the safe transportation of hazardous materials (hazmat).</p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary to promulgate regulations or issue orders to require, in cases where two or more railroads jointly operate within a small geographic area, all such host railroads to develop uniform operating rules for all operations within the area.</p> <p>Reauthorizes appropriations for the railroad safety technology grants program for FY2015-FY2020.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary and the Chairman of the Federal Communications Commission to coordinate to assess electromagnetic spectrum needs and availability for implementing positive train control systems.</p> <p>Requires a working alerter in the controlling locomotive of each intercity rail passenger train.</p> <p>Requires each Class I railroad carrier and each railroad carrier that provides intercity rail passenger or commuter rail passenger transportation to install inward- and outward-facing audio and image recording devices in all controlling locomotive cabs and cab car operating compartments. </p> <p>Requires the Secretary to promulgate regulations to implement the requirement for a fatigue management plan.</p> <p>Prescribes certain requirements for the operation of high-hazard flammable trains, including installation of wayside defective bearing detectors.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to require approval of each oil spill prevention and response plan submitted to the Administrator of the Federal Railroad Administration (FRA) (for tank cars) to ensure it meets all Department of Transportation (DOT) requirements.</p> <p>Revises positive train control systems requirements.</p> <p>Requires each Class I railroad carrier and each entity providing intercity or commuter rail passenger carrier transportation to develop and submit to the Secretary a plan for implementing a positive train control system by December 31, 2015, on its main line over which 20 or more tank cars loaded with petroleum crude oil are transported.</p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary to award grants to private or nonprofit organizations involved in, or affiliated with, transportation by regional (Class II) railroads and shortline (Class III) railroads for research, development, evaluation, and training efforts to enhance rail safety practices and safety culture. </p> <p>Requires the Secretary to conduct accident analysis and mitigation research on the safety risks of transporting energy products by rail.</p> <p>Prescribes requirements for: </p> <ul> <li>repair and replacement of damaged track inspection equipment;</li> <li>high density commuter rail track, automated track geometry, and automated train control inspections; and </li> <li>the securement of unattended freight train and vehicle equipment.</li> </ul> <p>Directs the Secretary to develop:</p> <ul> <li> an implementation plan for oversight of railroad safety risk reduction programs, and </li> <li>a long-range strategic human capital plan for the FRA.</li> </ul> <p>Revises and increases civil penalties for violations of rail safety regulations, DOT orders, accident and incident reporting or investigation requirements, as well as employee hours of service and sleeping quarters requirements.</p> <p>Requires reports to Congress on the progress of Metro-North Commuter Railroad in implementing certain directives and recommendations.</p> <p>Repeals the requirement for an FRA study of the use of reports and studies.</p> <p>Requires each Class I railroad carrier, each railroad carrier that has inadequate safety performance, and each railroad carrier that provides intercity rail passenger or commuter rail passenger transportation to establish a confidential close call reporting system.</p> <p>Prohibits a freight train or light engine used to move freight from operating unless it has a crew of at least two individuals of which: </p> <ul> <li>one is certified as a locomotive operator, and</li> <li>one is certified as a train conductor.</li> </ul>]]></text>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <introducedDate>2014-09-10</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <committeeReports />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-09-10</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <committee />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2014-09-10</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <recordedVotes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

