<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <introducedDate>2013-05-21</introducedDate>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights Act - Amends the Older Americans Act of 1965 to make it the duty of the Assistant Secretary of Aging, acting through the designee responsible for elder abuse prevention and services, to: (1) establish best practices for state-based enforcement of a Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights through a Plan for Enforcement, (2) assist states with the development of such Bills of Rights and Plans for Enforcement to support the shift from institutional care to home and community-based long-term care (LTC) services, and (3) develop and use a process for review and approval of state Home Care Consumer Bills of Rights and Plans for Enforcement.</p> <p>Establishes additional state plan requirements,including that a state have a Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights and a Plan for Enforcement.</p> <p>Requires the Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights to address a home care consumer's right to: (1) basic safety; (2) information access; (3) choice, participation, and self-determination; (4) care and services provided in a way that promotes each consumer's dignity and individuality; and (5) redress of grievances. Requires the Bill of Rights also to address the role and responsibilities that fiduciaries may have in securing these rights of home care consumers.</p> <p>Requires that any allotment for vulnerable elder rights protection activities be used to develop a State Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights and Plan for Enforcement.</p> <p>Directs the Assistant Secretary to establish a National Adult Protective Services Resources Center to: (1) improve the capacity of state and local adult protective services programs, and (2) coordinate with the Home Care Ombudsman Program and Long-Term Care Ombudsman Program to protect home care consumers and residents of LTC facilities most effectively. </p> <p>Authorizes appropriations for State Home Care Ombudsman Programs. Directs the Assistant Secretary of Aging to award competitive grants to states for such Programs.</p> <p>Requires the Assistant Secretary of Aging, in implementing Aging and Disability Resource Centers in all states, to: (1) provide quality measures information about home and community-based LTC programs, service providers, and resources when referring consumers to them; and (2) identify measures of quality for such programs, providers, and resources.</p> <p>Requires the designated state agency, in promoting a comprehensive, coordinated state system enabling older individuals to receive LTC in home and community-based settings, to provide for distribution of quality measures information about home and community-based LTC programs, service providers, and resources.</p> <p><BR> </p>]]></text>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <actionDate>2013-05-21</actionDate>
          <updateDate>2013-05-21T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-06-04T20:56:15Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-05-21T19:43:57Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:24:37Z</updateDate>
    <amendments />
    <title>Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights Act</title>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Health</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Aging</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Consumer affairs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Crime prevention</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health care coverage and access</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health care quality</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health information and medical records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health programs administration and funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Home and outpatient care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>State and local government operations</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2013-05-21</actionDate>
    </latestAction>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <createDate>2013-05-22T07:02:04Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <laws />
    <relatedBills />
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-05-21</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2013-05-21</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <billNumber>998</billNumber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Blumenthal, Richard [D-CT]</fullName>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>B001277</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>2076</lisID>
          <gpoId>8332</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>B001277</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-05-21</sponsorshipDate>
        <lastName>Blumenthal</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>CT</state>
        <firstName>Richard</firstName>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <notes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Health</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights Act</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to amend the Older Americans Act of 1965 to establish a Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights, to establish State Home Care Ombudsman Programs, and for other purposes.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Home Care Consumer Bill of Rights Act</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <party>D</party>
        <middleName />
        <bioguideId>F000457</bioguideId>
        <state>MN</state>
        <byRequestType />
        <firstName>Al</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8339</gpoId>
          <lisID>1969</lisID>
          <bioguideId>F000457</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <fullName>Sen. Franken, Al [D-MN]</fullName>
        <lastName>Franken</lastName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

