<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <committee />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <introducedDate>2014-07-31</introducedDate>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:31:54Z</updateDate>
    <createDate>2014-08-01T10:29:47Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <subcommittees />
          <type>Standing</type>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-07-31T15:25:30Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <cosponsors />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <title>SAFE PLAY Act</title>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>SAFE PLAY Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Supporting Athletes, Families and Educators to Protect the Lives of Athletic Youth Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to promote youth athletic safety and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>SAFE PLAY Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <committeeReports />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2015-01-20T16:54:02Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Supporting Athletes, Families and Educators to Protect the Lives of Athletic Youth Act or the SAFE PLAY Act - Amends the Public Health Service Act to require the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) to develop public education and awareness materials and resources concerning cardiac health, including:</p> <ul> <li>information to increase education and awareness of high risk cardiac conditions and genetic heart rhythm abnormalities that may cause sudden cardiac arrest in children, adolescents, and young adults; </li> <li>sudden cardiac arrest and cardiomyopathy risk assessment worksheets to increase awareness of warning signs of, and increase the likelihood of early detection and treatment of, life-threatening cardiac conditions; </li> <li>training materials for emergency interventions and use of life-saving emergency equipment; and </li> <li>recommendations for how schools, childcare centers, and local youth athletic organizations can develop and implement cardiac emergency response plans.</li> </ul> <p>Requires the Director to: (1) provide for dissemination of such information to school personnel, coaches, and families; and (2) develop data collection methods to determine the degree to which such persons have an understanding of cardiac issues.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary of Health and Human Services (HHS) to award grants to enable eligible local educational agencies (LEAs) and schools served by such LEAs to purchase AEDs and implement nationally recognized CPR and AED training courses.</p> <p>Amends the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 to require a state, as a condition of receiving funds under such Act, to certify that it requires: (1) LEAs to implement a standard plan for concussion safety and management for public schools; (2) public schools to post information on the symptoms of, the risks posed by, and the actions a student should take in response to, a concussion; (3) public school personnel who suspect a student has sustained a concussion in a school-sponsored activity to notify the parents and prohibit the student from participating in such activity until they receive a written release from a health care professional; and (4) a public school's concussion management team to ensure that a student who has sustained a concussion is receiving appropriate academic supports.</p> <p>Directs the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) to develop public education and awareness materials and resources to be disseminated to schools regarding risks from exposure to excessive heat and humidity and recommendations for how to avoid heat-related illness. Requires public schools to develop excessive heat action plans for school-sponsored athletic activities.</p> <p>Requires the Director to develop guidelines for the development of emergency action plans for youth athletics. </p> <p>Authorizes the Commissioner of Food and Drugs (FDA) to develop information about the ingredients used in energy drinks and their potential side effects, and recommend guidelines for the safe use of such drinks by youth, for dissemination to public schools.</p> <p>Requires the Director to: (1) expand, intensify, and coordinate CDC activities regarding cardiac conditions, concussions, and heat-related illnesses among youth athletes; and (2) report on fatalities and catastrophic injuries among youths participating an athletic activities.</p>]]></text>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <updateDate>2014-07-31T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <notes />
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <recordedVotes />
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-11-17</actionDate>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Early Childhood, Elementary, and Secondary Education.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>SAFE PLAY Act</latestTitle>
        <number>5324</number>
      </item>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-01-22</actionDate>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Early Childhood, Elementary, and Secondary Education.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Protecting Student Athletes From Concussions Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <number>3532</number>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Atmospheric science and weather</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Cardiovascular and respiratory health</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Child health</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Child safety and welfare</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Health and Human Services</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Education programs funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Elementary and secondary education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Emergency communications systems</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Emergency medical services and trauma care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>First responders and emergency personnel</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Food supply, safety, and labeling</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health information and medical records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health programs administration and funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health promotion and preventive care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health technology, devices, supplies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medical research</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Neurological disorders</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Nutrition and diet</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Research administration and funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>School administration</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>School athletics</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Special education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Teaching, teachers, curricula</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Health</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <laws />
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
      <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
    </latestAction>
    <billNumber>2718</billNumber>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Health</name>
    </policyArea>
    <amendments />
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <firstName>ROBERT</firstName>
        <party>D</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Menendez, Robert [D-NJ]</fullName>
        <bioguideId>M000639</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>791</lisID>
          <gpoId>8239</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>M000639</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>MENENDEZ</lastName>
        <middleName />
        <state>NJ</state>
        <byRequestType />
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <calendarNumbers />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

