<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <cosponsors />
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Education</name>
    </policyArea>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:24:19Z</updateDate>
    <recordedVotes />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <createDate>2013-05-15T07:02:14Z</createDate>
    <committeeReports />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Graduation Promise Act of 2013 - Authorizes the Secretary of Education to make matching grants to states and, through them, subgrants to local educational agencies (LEAs) for differentiated high school improvement systems targeting support to schools with low student achievement and graduation rates after such schools fail for two consecutive years to make annual measurable growth pursuant to state academic performance standards. Allots grant funds to states pursuant to a formula that favors states with low graduation rates and a high percentage of students attending low-income LEAs.</p> <p>Requires state grantees to establish comprehensive school performance indicators and minimum annual improvement benchmarks for use, in addition to annual measurable growth indicators, in analyzing school performance and determining the improvement category into which a school is placed.</p> <p> Directs LEA subgrantees to: (1) categorize each of their schools that fail to make annual measurable growth for two consecutive years as needing targeted intervention, whole school reforms, or replacement; (2) convene a local school improvement team for each of such schools that will use school performance indicators, annual measurable growth indicators, and other relevant data to conduct a school needs assessment and develop a multiyear school improvement plan tailored to the school's need categorization; and (3) support the successful implementation of such plans and district-wide high school improvement strategies. </p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary to award competitive grants to LEAs, nonprofit organizations, and institutions of higher education to develop and implement, or replicate, effective secondary school models for struggling students and dropouts.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-05-14T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-06-11T22:05:09Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-05-14</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Academic performance and assessments</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Education of the disadvantaged</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Education programs funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Elementary and secondary education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Higher education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>School administration</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Special education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Teaching, teachers, curricula</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Vocational and technical education</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Education</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <notes />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-05-14</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <committee />
        <actionDate>2013-05-14</actionDate>
        <links />
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <relatedBills />
    <title>Graduation Promise Act of 2013</title>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <laws />
    <billNumber>940</billNumber>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <introducedDate>2013-05-14</introducedDate>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2013-05-14</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-05-14T15:17:12Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <state>NM</state>
        <bioguideId>U000039</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8260</gpoId>
          <lisID>1567</lisID>
          <bioguideId>U000039</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>D</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Udall, Tom [D-NM]</fullName>
        <firstName>TOM</firstName>
        <lastName>UDALL</lastName>
        <middleName />
        <byRequestType />
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <title>Graduation Promise Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>A bill to provide grants to States to improve high schools and raise graduation rates while ensuring rigorous standards, to develop and implement effective school models for struggling students and dropouts, and to improve State policies to raise graduation rates, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Graduation Promise Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <amendments />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

