<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <relatedBills />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:26:33Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <subcommittees />
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2013-08-01T17:07:58Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Bennet, Michael F. [D-CO]</fullName>
        <middleName>F.</middleName>
        <bioguideId>B001267</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1965</lisID>
          <bioguideId>B001267</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8302</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <lastName>Bennet</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>CO</state>
        <firstName>Michael</firstName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Emergency Management</name>
    </policyArea>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2013-08-01</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <party>R</party>
        <middleName>D.</middleName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>C000880</bioguideId>
        <firstName>MICHAEL</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>250</lisID>
          <gpoId>8289</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>C000880</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <state>ID</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-08-01</sponsorshipDate>
        <fullName>Sen. Crapo, Mike [R-ID]</fullName>
        <lastName>CRAPO</lastName>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <billNumber>1428</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>PREPARE Act of 2013</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Prepare, Ready, Equip, and Prevent Areas at Risk of Emergency Wildfires Act of 2013</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>A bill to amend the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act to provide for wildfire mitigation grants, and for other purposes.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>PREPARE Act of 2013</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <createDate>2013-08-02T05:52:42Z</createDate>
    <notes />
    <title>PREPARE Act of 2013</title>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Emergency planning and evacuation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Fires</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Forests, forestry, trees</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Emergency Management</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Prepare, Ready, Equip, and Prevent Areas at Risk of Emergency Wildfires Act of 2013 or the PREPARE Act of 2013 - Amends the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act to direct the President, acting through the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA), to establish a pilot program to make grants to states for wildfire mitigation and preparedness.</p> <p>Permits a grant to be used to: (1) reduce the use of fuels that may contribute to catastrophic wildfires in high-risk areas; (2) invest in personnel, organizations, vehicles, and equipment to improve wildfire preparedness; (3) invest in airborne assets to help contain, suppress, and monitor wildfires; and (4) prevent damage from runoff into waterways and floods caused by erosion from wildfires.</p> <p>Makes a state eligible for assistance under this Act if the fire management assistance grant ratio for such state is equal to or greater than 150% of the state population ratio. Authorizes the President to waive that requirement if a state: (1) files a petition for waiver of that requirement, and (2) demonstrates that significant environmental changes or shifts in forest health put the state at an elevated risk for catastrophic wildfires.</p> <p>Allows the governor of a state to award grant funds to: (1) any county or municipality in that state with a community wildfire protection plan or a local mitigation plan, or (2) any other entity that is explicitly referenced in and central to the design of such a plan.</p> <p>Directs the President to consider environmental conditions in a state and give preference to a state: (1) with a high level of need for assistance based on the best scientific data available, (2) a state that provides 100% matching non-federal funds, and (3) a state that previously received a grant and efficiently and effectively used the federal funds for wildfire mitigation and preparedness activities. </p> <p>Directs the President to use specified unobligated amounts in the National Predisaster Mitigation Fund for each of FY2014-FY2019 in carrying out this Act.</p>]]></text>
          <actionDate>2013-08-01</actionDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <updateDate>2013-08-01T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-11-19T23:09:39Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <introducedDate>2013-08-01</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <committeeReports />
    <actions>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-08-01</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <actionDate>2013-08-01</actionDate>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <links />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <recordedVotes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

