<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <number>5364</number>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>CHIP Extension and Improvement Act of 2014</latestTitle>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Health.</text>
          <actionDate>2014-08-01</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:30:51Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-06-11T16:55:50Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <name>Finance Committee</name>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>ssfi00</systemCode>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Rockefeller, John D., IV [D-WV]</fullName>
        <middleName />
        <bioguideId>R000361</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>R000361</bioguideId>
          <lisID>1424</lisID>
          <gpoId>8273</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <lastName>ROCKEFELLER</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>WV</state>
        <firstName>JAY</firstName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Health</name>
    </policyArea>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2014-06-11</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Finance.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors />
    <billNumber>2461</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <title>CHIP Extension Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>A bill to amend title XXI of the Social Security Act to extend and improve the Children's Health Insurance Program, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>CHIP Extension Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <createDate>2014-06-12T07:19:57Z</createDate>
    <notes />
    <title>CHIP Extension Act of 2014</title>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Health</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Adoption and foster care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Advisory bodies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Appropriations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Child health</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Dental care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Disability and paralysis</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Employee benefits and pensions</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Foreign language and bilingual programs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government employee pay, benefits, personnel management</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government trust funds</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health care costs and insurance</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health care coverage and access</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health care quality</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health information and medical records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health programs administration and funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health promotion and preventive care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Immunology and vaccination</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Juvenile crime and gang violence</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medicaid</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medical tests and diagnostic methods</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Performance measurement</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Poverty and welfare assistance</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>State and local government operations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Women's health</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-07-14T19:23:40Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>CHIP Extension Act of 2014 - Revises and extends through FY2019 at generally increased levels the program under title XXI (State Children's Health Insurance) (CHIP) of the Social Security Act (SSA), and adjusts CHIP allotment requirements accordingly, including the rebasing and growth factor update rules for computing state allotments.</p>Sets forth new requirements for the enrollment and retention of children for fiscal years after FY2014. <p>Establishes in the Treasury the CHIP Shortfall Fund, which shall be available without further appropriations for payments to shortfall states whose projected CHIP expenditures for the fiscal year will exceed a specified amount. </p> <p>Gives states the option to increase up to 26 the upper age limit for CHIP-eligible children with special health care needs.</p> <p>Requires a state to establish procedures to eliminate gaps in coverage and to assist a child's and pregnant woman's transition: (1)&nbsp; from coverage under the state plan under SSA title XIX (Medicaid) or the state CHIP plan to coverage under a qualified health plan offered through an Exchange, and (2) from coverage under a qualified health plan to coverage under a state Medicaid or CHIP plan.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to develop comparability standards with respect to affordability, benefits, and network adequacy which qualified health plans offered by a state-established Exchange must meet to be certified for such transitions.</p>  <p>Amends the Internal Revenue Code, with respect to minimum essential coverage for a targeted pregnant low-income woman under CHIP, to exclude from such coverage, at a woman's option, pregnancy-related assistance.</p> <p>Provides automaticenrollment under CHIP for newborns.</p> <p>Amends SSA title XIX (Medicaid) to give states the option to extend express lane eligibility to pregnant women.</p> <p>Makes permanent the express lane option and the CHIP outreach and enrollment grant program.</p> <p>Requires a national campaign to increase enrollment in CHIP or Medicaid of children from families that speak a language other than English.</p> <p>Limits to 5% of family income the total annual aggregate amount of any premium, enrollment fee, deduction or other cost sharing imposed under a Medicaid plan with respect to individuals and their families..</p> <p>Amends SSA title XXI to prohibit cost-sharing for pregnancy-related assistance. Imposes under CHIP a certain limit on cost-sharing for dental-only supplemental coverage. </p> <p>Amends SSA titles XIX and XXI to cover preventive services for children or pregnant women without cost-sharing.</p> <p>Amends SSA title XIX to cover newly approved vaccines within 30 days after the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices approves them.</p> <p>Treats CHIP-eligible children as federally vaccine-eligible children.</p> <p>Makes permanent the program for the distribution of pediatric vaccines.</p>  <p>Amends SSA title XI to extend the pediatric quality measures program. Requires the Secretary to establish a program to continue and enhance pediatric quality measures program centers of excellence.</p> <p>Revises requirements for initial core measures.</p>  <p>Directs the Secretary to convene a panel of health experts to establish priorities and goals for child health as recommended in a specified report by the Institute of Medicine.</p> <p>Modifies and extends the Demonstration Projects for Improving the Quality of Children's Health Care and the Use of Health Information Technology.</p> <p>Extends funding for Childhood Obesity Demonstration Projects and maternal, infant, and early childhood home visiting programs. </p> <p>Directs the Comptroller General (GAO) to study each state in which individuals eligible for Medicaid or CHIP are provided such assistance through enrollment in a qualified health plan or employer-sponsored insurance.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2014-06-11T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <actionDate>2014-06-11</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <introducedDate>2014-06-11</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <committeeReports />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-06-11</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssfi00</systemCode>
          <name>Finance Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Finance.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2014-06-11</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <recordedVotes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

