<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:25:10Z</updateDate>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>Building upon Unique Indian Learning and Development Act</title>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>A bill to strengthen Indian education, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>Building upon Unique Indian Learning and Development Act</title>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <lastName>UDALL</lastName>
        <firstName>TOM</firstName>
        <bioguideId>U000039</bioguideId>
        <middleName />
        <state>NM</state>
        <fullName>Sen. Udall, Tom [D-NM]</fullName>
        <party>D</party>
        <byRequestType />
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>U000039</bioguideId>
          <lisID>1567</lisID>
          <gpoId>8260</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <introducedDate>2013-06-11</introducedDate>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Building upon Unique Indian Learning and Development Act - Directs the Secretary of the Interior to establish an in-school facility innovation program contest to encourage institutions of higher education (IHEs) to solve the problem of how to improve Indian school facilities for problem-based learning.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary of Education (Secretary) and the Secretary of the Interior to establish a Department of the Interior and Department of Education Joint Oversight Board to coordinate Indian education policies and assistance.</p> <p>Amends part A (Indian Education) of title VII (Indian, Native Hawaiian, and Alaska Native Education) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (ESEA) to establish a program awarding grants to local educational agencies (LEAs), IHEs, or nonprofit organizations to create or expand teacher and administrator pipelines for teachers and administrators of Native American students.</p> <p>Amends the school improvement program, under part A of title I of the ESEA, to require states to develop standards-based assessments and classroom lessons that accommodate diverse learning styles.</p> <p>Directs: (1) the Secretary to expand programs for Native American school children to support learning in the children's Native language and culture and provide English language instruction, and (2) the Comptroller General to conduct research on culture- and language-based education to identify the factors that improve education and health outcomes.</p> <p>Excepts Native language teachers from the requirement that teachers be highly qualified. Requires states, in collaboration with Indian tribes or Tribal Colleges and Universities, to develop an alternative licensure or certification process for those teachers.</p> <p>Directs the Commissioner of the Administration for Native Americans in the Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) to establish a program providing grants to public and nonprofit private agencies to assist Native Americans in ensuring the survival and continuing vitality of Native American languages.</p> <p>Requires Department of Education assistance programs for elementary and secondary schools or early learning programs to reserve at least 0.5% of their funding for Indian elementary and secondary schools or early learning programs.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary to: (1) establish a program to improve school environments and student skill development for healthy choices for Native American students, (2) establish a program for school dropout prevention for Native American students, and (3) collaborate with the Secretary of Agriculture (USDA) to establish tribal-school specific school gardens and nutrition programs that are within the tribal cultural context.</p> <p>Authorizes and appropriates additional funds for the Impact Aid program, under title VIII of the ESEA, through FY2016. (The Impact Aid program compensates LEAs for the financial burden of federal activities affecting their school districts.) </p> <p>Authorizes appropriations for FY2014, for use through FY2015, for: (1) the tribally controlled postsecondary career and technical institutions program under the Tribally Controlled Colleges and Universities Assistance Act of 1978; (2) the Institute of American Indian and Alaska Native Culture and Arts Development; (3) institutional operations grants for the Haskell Indian Nations University and Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute under the Snyder Act; and (4) scholarships and adult education and special higher education scholarships under the Snyder Act. </p> <UL> </UL>]]></text>
          <actionDate>2013-06-11</actionDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <updateDate>2013-06-11T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2015-03-30T19:46:51Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Native Americans</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Academic performance and assessments</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Alaska Natives and Hawaiians</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Building construction</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Child health</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of the Interior</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Education programs funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Educational facilities and institutions</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Elementary and secondary education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Executive agency funding and structure</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Foreign language and bilingual programs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health programs administration and funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health promotion and preventive care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Higher education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Indian social and development programs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Licensing and registrations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Minority education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Nutrition and diet</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Preschool education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>School administration</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Science and engineering education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Student aid and college costs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Teaching, teachers, curricula</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Vocational and technical education</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <middleName />
        <state>NM</state>
        <firstName>Martin</firstName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>H001046</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Heinrich, Martin [D-NM]</fullName>
        <lastName>Heinrich</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-06-11</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1937</lisID>
          <bioguideId>H001046</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8056</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-06-11</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>slia00</systemCode>
          <name>Indian Affairs Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Indian Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <committee />
        <actionDate>2013-06-11</actionDate>
        <links />
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <title>Building upon Unique Indian Learning and Development Act</title>
    <createDate>2013-06-12T07:01:25Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2013-06-11</actionDate>
      <links />
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Indian Affairs.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Native Americans</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billNumber>1131</billNumber>
    <laws />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Higher Education and Workforce Training.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-07-08</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>Building upon Unique Indian Learning and Development Act</latestTitle>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <number>2367</number>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>slia00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-06-11T16:10:59Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <type>Other</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Indian Affairs Committee</name>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <committeeReports />
    <notes />
    <amendments />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

