<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <title>Motor Vehicle and Highway Safety Enhancement Act of 2014</title>
    <createDate>2014-08-01T10:29:47Z</createDate>
    <billNumber>2760</billNumber>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>M001170</bioguideId>
        <middleName />
        <fullName>Sen. McCaskill, Claire [D-MO]</fullName>
        <firstName>Claire</firstName>
        <byRequestType />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1820</lisID>
          <bioguideId>M001170</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8252</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>McCaskill</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>MO</state>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <cosponsors />
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <number>2819</number>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-09-16</actionDate>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>Raechel and Jacqueline Houck Safe Rental Car Act of 2014</latestTitle>
      </item>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <number>921</number>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-09-15</actionDate>
          <text>Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 561.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>Raechel and Jacqueline Houck Safe Rental Car Act of 2013</latestTitle>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <title>Raechel and Jacqueline Houck Safe Rental Car Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Motor Vehicle and Highway Safety Enhancement Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to extend National Highway Traffic Safety Administration authorizations, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Motor Vehicle and Highway Safety Enhancement Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <introducedDate>2014-07-31</introducedDate>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
      <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <amendments />
    <committeeReports />
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Bankruptcy</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Business records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Consumer affairs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Corporate finance and management</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Fraud offenses and financial crimes</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government trust funds</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Lease and rental services</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Licensing and registrations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Motor vehicles</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Product safety and quality</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Research administration and funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Research and development</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Roads and highways</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation programs funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation safety and security</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <laws />
    <notes />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <committee />
        <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <links />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <recordedVotes />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Motor Vehicle and Highway Safety Enhancement Act of 2014 - Authorizes appropriations out of the Highway Trust Fund (HTF) (other than the Mass Transit Account) for specified National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA) safety programs (including administrative expenses) for FY2015-FY2020.</p> <p>Revises uniform guidelines for state highway safety programs to require programs to: (1) reduce injuries and deaths to older drivers, and (2) improve emergency medical services response to crash sites.</p>   <p>Revises grant eligibility requirements for states that adopt and enforce mandatory alcohol-ignition interlock laws to allow them to make certain exceptions to the requirement. </p>   <p>Declares that the federal share of costs for highway safety research and development projects may be up to 100% if so specified in the project agreement.</p> <p>Revises the allocation of grant amounts to a state for a fiscal year for motorcyclist safety programs. </p>  <p>Extends for FY2015-FY2020 the authorization of appropriations for NHTSA motor vehicle safety programs in general.</p> <p>Revises and increases civil and criminal penalties for persons who violate motor vehicle safety regulations.</p> <p>Raechel and Jacqueline Houck Safe Rental Car Act of 2014 - Authorizes a rental company that receives a notification (approved by NHTSA) from the manufacturer of a covered rental vehicle about any equipment defect, or noncompliance with federal motor vehicle safety standards, to rent or sell the vehicle or equipment only if the defect or noncompliance is remedied.</p> <p>Specifies any rental vehicle: (1) rated at 10,000 pounds gross vehicle weight or less, (2) rented without a driver for an initial term of under 4 months, and (3) that is part of a motor vehicle fleet of 5 or more motor vehicles used for rental purposes by a rental company.</p> <p>Prescribes a special rule to require rental companies to comply with specified limitations on sale, lease, or rental of a motor vehicle as soon as practicable, but within 24 hours after the earliest receipt of the manufacturer's notification of a defect or noncompliance with vehicle safety standards, whether by electronic means or first class mail. Extends the 24-hour deadline for complying with such limitations to 48 hours if the notification covers more than 5,000 motor vehicles in the rental company's fleet.</p> <p>Permits a rental company to rent (but not sell or lease) a motor vehicle subject to recall if the defect or noncompliance remedy is not immediately available and the company takes any actions specified in the notice to alter the vehicle temporarily to eliminate the safety risk posed.</p> <p>Makes these special rules for rental companies inapplicable to junk automobiles.</p> <p>Prohibits a rental company from knowingly making inoperable any safety devices or elements of design installed on or in a compliant motor vehicle or vehicle equipment unless the company reasonably believes the vehicle or equipment will not be used when the devices or elements are inoperable.</p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary, upon request, to inspect records of a rental company with respect to a safety investigation. Authorizes the Secretary to require a rental company to keep records or make reports for purposes of compliance with federal motor vehicle safety orders or regulations.</p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary to study the effectiveness of the amendments made by this Act and of other activities of rental companies.</p> <p>Amends the Moving Ahead for Progress in the 21st Century Act (MAP-21) to require the mandatory study of the safety of rental trucks during a specified seven-year period to evaluate the completion of safety recall remedies on rental trucks.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to solicit comments regarding the implementation of this Act from members of the public, including rental companies, consumer organizations, automobile manufacturers, and automobile dealers.</p> <p>Declares that nothing in this Act shall: (1) be construed to create or increase any liability for a manufacturer who manufactures or imports a motor vehicle that is subject to defect or noncompliance recall requirements; or (2) supersede or otherwise affect the contractual obligations, if any, between such manufacturer and a rental company.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2014-07-31T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-10-24T14:49:05Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:32:04Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-07-31T21:23:21Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <subcommittees />
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
    </policyArea>
    <calendarNumbers />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

