<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <relatedBills />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:22:12Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-03-20T21:39:52Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Sanders, Bernard [I-VT]</fullName>
        <middleName />
        <bioguideId>S000033</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1010</lisID>
          <bioguideId>S000033</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8270</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <lastName>SANDERS</lastName>
        <party>I</party>
        <state>VT</state>
        <firstName>BERNARD</firstName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Health</name>
    </policyArea>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2013-03-20</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors />
    <billNumber>627</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>Medical Innovation Prize Fund Act</title>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>A bill to provide incentives for investment in research and development for new medicines, to enhance access to new medicines, and for other purposes.</title>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>Medical Innovation Prize Fund Act</title>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <createDate>2013-03-21T08:01:14Z</createDate>
    <notes />
    <title>Medical Innovation Prize Fund Act</title>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Health</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Advanced technology and technological innovations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Advisory bodies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Drug safety, medical device, and laboratory regulation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health care costs and insurance</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Immunology and vaccination</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Insurance industry and regulation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Intellectual property</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Manufacturing</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Marketing and advertising</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medical research</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Prescription drugs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Research administration and funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Research and development</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>User charges and fees</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDate>2013-03-20</actionDate>
          <updateDate>2013-03-20T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-05-28T20:52:39Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Medical Innovation Prize Fund Act - Denies any person the exclusive right to manufacture, distribute, sell, or use in interstate commerce a drug, a biological product, or a drug or biological product manufacturing process, including the exclusive right to rely on health registration data or the 30-month stay-of-effectiveness period for Orange Book patents. Prescribes remuneration, in the form of prize payments from a Fund for Medical Innovation Prizes, in lieu of such market exclusivity.</p> <p>Establishes: (1) the Fund for Medical Innovation Prizes; and (2) a Board of Trustees for such Fund, which shall award prize payments for medical innovation and establish independent expert advisory committees.</p> <p>Directs the Board to award prize payments for medical innovation relating to a drug, a biological product, or a new manufacturing process for a drug or biological product to: (1) the first person to receive market clearance with respect to the drug or biological product; (2) the holder of the patent with respect to a manufacturing process; or (3) persons or communities that as an open source contribution openly shared knowledge, data, materials, and technology on a royalty-free and nondiscriminatory basis.</p> <p>Requires the Board to establish and periodically modify minimum levels of funding for such awards for priority research and development, including global neglected diseases, orphan diseases, and global infectious diseases and other global public health priorities.</p> <p>Allows the Board of Trustees to authorize multiple nonprofit intermediaries to reward projects for interim research and development of products or for open source dividend prizes.</p>  <p>Requires the Comptroller General (GAO) to conduct annual audits to determine the Board's effectiveness in bringing to market new drugs, vaccines, biological products, and manufacturing processes in a cost-effective manner and in addressing society's global medical needs.</p> <p>Establishes an annual fee for health insurers to fund this Act.</p>]]></text>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <introducedDate>2013-03-20</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <committeeReports />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-03-20</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sshr00</systemCode>
          <name>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <committee />
        <actionDate>2013-03-20</actionDate>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <links />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <recordedVotes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

