<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>M001183</bioguideId>
        <state>WV</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-05-22</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
        <firstName>Joe</firstName>
        <party>D</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Manchin, Joe, III [D-WV]</fullName>
        <lastName>Manchin</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1983</lisID>
          <bioguideId>M001183</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8256</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Energy</name>
    </policyArea>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:24:43Z</updateDate>
    <recordedVotes />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <createDate>2013-05-23T07:02:05Z</createDate>
    <committeeReports />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <updateDate>2013-05-22T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>All-Of-The-Above Federal Building Energy Conservation Act of 2013 - Amends the National Energy Conservation Policy Act to extend energy performance requirements for federal buildings for each of FY2016-FY2020 (from a 33% reduction from 2003 energy consumption level for FY2015 to a 45% reduction for FY2020).</p> <p>Requires agencies to report to the Secretary of Energy (DOE) on buildings that carry out energy intensive activities and that are designated by the agency for exclusion from such requirements.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary to review the results of the implementation of such requirements by December 31, 2016, (currently, December 31, 2013).</p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary to amend or set such performance requirements for each of FY2018-FY2025 by a rule that: (1) requires a cost-benefit analysis and an opportunity for public comment, (2) establishes performance levels that are technically feasible and economically justifiable, and (3) considers any energy- and water-saving measures identified in energy and water evaluations.</p> <p>Requires designated facility energy managers to consider using a system to manage energy use at their facilities in accordance with the International Organization for Standardization standard numbered 50001 and entitled &quot;Energy Management Systems.&quot;</p> <p>Establishes exemptions from energy and water evaluation requirements. Requires energy managers, as part of the web-based certification, to explain the reasons why any life-cycle cost effective measures identified in such evaluation were not implemented. Requires the Secretary to make available a report that summarizes information tracked under such certification.</p> <p> Amends the Energy Conservation and Production Act to revise the definition of &quot;federal building&quot; to include buildings altered by federal agencies, and to define &quot;major renovation,&quot; for purposes of such Act. Requires the Secretary to establish revised federal building energy efficiency performance standards after the approval of revisions of ASHRAE Standard 90.1 or the International Energy Conservation Code (IECC) to meet or exceed such revisions, including requiring, unless new or renovated federal buildings are demonstrated not to be life-cycle cost effective: (1) such buildings to be designed to achieve energy consumption levels that are at least 30% below the levels established in the ASHRAE Standard or the IECC, and (2) no less than 30% of the hot water demand for each new building or building undergoing a major renovation to be met through the installation and use of solar hot water heaters.</p> <p>Repeals: (1) a standard on fossil fuel-generated energy use in federal buildings, and (2) a requirement for the Secretary to review federal building energy standards every five years.</p>]]></text>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDate>2013-05-22</actionDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-07-22T20:13:32Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Building construction</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Energy</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Energy efficiency and conservation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government buildings, facilities, and property</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water use and supply</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Energy</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <notes />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-05-22</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssev00</systemCode>
          <name>Environment and Public Works Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Environment and Public Works.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <committee />
        <actionDate>2013-05-22</actionDate>
        <links />
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Committee on Energy and Natural Resources Subcommittee on Energy. Hearings held. With printed Hearing: S.Hrg. 113-70.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-06-25</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>All-Of-The-Above Federal Building Energy Conservation Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <number>1199</number>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <title>All-Of-The-Above Federal Building Energy Conservation Act of 2013</title>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <laws />
    <billNumber>1020</billNumber>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <introducedDate>2013-05-22</introducedDate>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2013-05-22</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Environment and Public Works.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>ssev00</systemCode>
          <subcommittees />
          <type>Standing</type>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <name>Environment and Public Works Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-05-22T19:46:33Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <state>ND</state>
        <bioguideId>H001061</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8331</gpoId>
          <lisID>2079</lisID>
          <bioguideId>H001061</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Hoeven, John [R-ND]</fullName>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <lastName>Hoeven</lastName>
        <middleName />
        <byRequestType />
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>All-Of-The-Above Federal Building Energy Conservation Act of 2013</title>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>A bill to improve energy performance in Federal buildings, and for other purposes.</title>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>All-Of-The-Above Federal Building Energy Conservation Act of 2013</title>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <amendments />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

