<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <introducedDate>2013-07-31</introducedDate>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Domestic Energy and Jobs Act <b>- </b>Gasoline Regulations Act of 2013 - Directs the President to establish the Transportation Fuels Regulatory Committee to analyze and report on the cumulative impacts of certain covered rules and actions under the Clean Air Act. </p><p>Prohibits the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) from finalizing specified rules until at least six months after the Committee submits its final report.</p> <p>Amends the Clean Air Act to: (1) authorize the Administrator to waive temporarily a control or prohibition governing the use of a regulated fuel or fuel additive following a determination that unusual and extreme fuel additive supply circumstances are the result of a problem with distribution or delivery equipment necessary for the transportation or delivery of fuel or fuel additives, and (2) grant a presumptive approval to a request for a waiver if the Administrator does not approve or deny such request within three days after its receipt. <p>Amends the Energy Policy Act of 2005 to direct the Administrator and the Secretary of Energy to include biofuels in their joint Fuel System Requirements Harmonization Study, as well as an assessment of the effect of such requirements upon achievement of the renewable fuel standard. <p>Planning for American Energy Act of 2013 - Amends the Mineral Leasing Act to direct the Secretary of the Interior (Secretary) and the Secretary of Agriculture (USDA) to publish every four years a Quadrennial Federal Onshore Energy Production Strategy. <p>Requires the Secretary to determine a domestic strategic production objective for the development of energy resources from federal onshore lands.</p> <p>Providing Leasing Certainty for American Energy Act of 2013 - Amends the Mineral Leasing Act to direct the Secretary, in conducting lease sales, to offer for sale at least 25% of the annual nominated acreage not previously made available for lease. </p> <p>Shields such acreage from review and the test of extraordinary circumstances. Makes such acreage eligible for certain categorical exclusions under the Energy Policy Act of 2005 in connection with review under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (NEPA).</p> <p>(A categorical exclusion is a category of actions which do not individually or cumulatively have a significant effect on the human environment and for which, as a consequence, neither an environmental assessment nor an environmental impact statement is required.)</p> <p>Prohibits the Secretary from: (1) withdrawing approval of any covered energy project involving a lease issued under the Act without finding a violation by the lessee of lease terms; (2) delaying indefinitely issuance of project approvals, drilling and seismic permits, and rights-of-way for activities under a lease; or (3) cancelling or withdrawing any lease parcel after a competitive lease sale has occurred and a winning bidder has made the last payment for the parcel.</p> <p>Declares without force or effect Bureau of Land Management Instruction Memorandum 2010-117. </p> <p>Streamlining Permitting of American Energy Act of 2013 - Amends the Mineral Leasing Act to revise requirements for the issuance of permits to drill in energy projects on federal lands.</p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary of the Interior to extend the initial 30-day permit application review period for up to 2 periods of 15 days each, if the Secretary has given written notice of the delay to the applicant. </p> <p>Deems a permit application approved if the Secretary has made no decision on it 60 days after its receipt.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to collect a single $6,500 permit processing fee per application from each applicant at the time the decision is made whether or not to issue a permit. </p> <p>Requires that 50% of fees collected as annual wind energy and solar energy right-of-way authorization fees be retained by the Secretary for specified uses.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary to collect a $5,000 documentation fee to accompany each appeal of an action on a lease, right-of-way, or application for permit to drill.</p> <p> Requires the Secretary to establish a Federal Permit Streamlining Project in each BLM Field office with responsibility for issuing permits energy projects on federal land.</p> <p>Prohibits the Secretary from requiring a finding of extraordinary circumstances related to a categorical exclusion in administering the Energy Policy Act of 2005 with respect to review under NEPA.</p> <p>National Petroleum Reserve Alaska Access Act - Amends the Naval Petroleum Reserves Production Act of 1976 to require that the mandatory program of competitive leasing of oil and gas in the National Petroleum Reserve (NPR) in Alaska include at least one lease sale annually in those NPR areas most likely to produce commercial quantities of oil and natural gas each year during 2013-2023.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to facilitate and ensure, according to a specified timeline, permits for all surface development activities (including pipelines and road construction).</p> <p>Instructs the Secretary to approve, within 180 days after enactment of this Act, and after public comment and consultation with the state of Alaska, right-of-way corridors for the construction of two separate additional bridges and pipeline rights-of-way to facilitate oil and gas development in the NPR.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary, through the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), to assess all technically recoverable fossil fuel resources within the NPR, including conventional and unconventional oil and natural gas. </p> <p>Declares without force or effect with respect to this title the designation by EPA of the Colville River Delta as an Aquatic Resource of National Importance.</p> <p>BLM Live Internet Auctions Act - Amends the Mineral Leasing Act to authorize the Secretary to conduct onshore oil and gas lease sales through Internet-based bidding methods.</p> <p> Advancing Offshore Wind Production Act - Exempts projects determined by the Secretary to be an offshore meteorological site testing and monitoring project from environmental impact statement requirements under NEPA.</p> <p> Defines an &quot;offshore meteorological site testing and monitoring project&quot; as a project administered by the Department of the Interior and carried out on or in the waters of the Outer Continental Shelf (OCS) to test or monitor weather (including wind, tidal, current, and solar energy) using towers, buoys, or other temporary ocean infrastructure and that meets specified other requirements.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to: (1) require that any applicant seeking to conduct an offshore meteorological site testing and monitoring project on the OCS obtain a permit and right of way for the project; and (2) decide whether to issue such a permit and right of way within 30 days after receiving an application.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary, acting through the USGS, to publish in the Federal Register a draft methodology for determining which minerals qualify as critical minerals, based upon an assessment of whether they are subject to potential supply restrictions and important in use.</p> <p>Directs the President to coordinate federal agency actions to facilitate development and production of domestic resources to meet national critical minerals needs.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to conduct a specified national assessment of critical minerals. </p> <p>Establishes within the Department of the Interior the Critical Minerals Working Group.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary of Energy (DOE) to conduct research and development to promote the efficient production, use, recycling of, and alternatives to critical minerals.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary of Labor to assess the domestic availability of technically trained personnel necessary for critical mineral enterprises.</p> <p>Directs the Secretaries of the Interior and of Labor to arrange jointly with the National Academy of Sciences (NAS) and the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) to coordinate with the National Science Foundation (NSF) on a study to design an interdisciplinary program on critical minerals that will support the critical mineral supply chain.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary of the Interior and the NSF to conduct jointly a competitive program of four-year grants to institutions of higher education to implement programs addressing integrated critical mineral education, training, innovation, and workforce development. </p> <p>Directs the Secretary of State to promote international cooperation with U.S. allies regarding critical mineral supply chain issues. </p> <p>Repeals the National Critical Materials Act of 1984.</p> <p>Prohibits the Secretary of the Interior from transferring to the Office of Surface Mining Reclamation and Enforcement any responsibility or authority to perform any function performed on the day before enactment of this Act under the solid minerals leasing program of the Department of the Interior.</p> <p>Amends the Gulf of Mexico Energy Security Act of 2006 to: (1) reduce from FY2055 to FY2025 the time period during which the maximum amount of distributed qualified OCS shelf revenues available for distribution to certain states remains $500 million, and (2) increase to $750 million the maximum amount of distributed qualified OCS revenues for each of FY2026-FY2055.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to carry out Lease Sale 220 off the coast of Virginia within the proposed OCS oil and gas leasing program for the 2012-2017 period.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary and the Secretary of Defense (DOD) to work jointly to: (1) preserve the ability of the Armed Forces to maintain an optimum state of readiness through their continued use of OCS energy resources; and (2) allow effective exploration, development, and production of U.S. oil, gas, and renewable energy resources.</p> <p>Prohibits any exploration, development, or production of oil or natural gas off the coast of Virginia that would conflict with any military operation agreed upon in a certain Memorandum.</p> <p>Prohibits the Secretary of the Interior, before December 31, 2013, from issuing a regulation modifying the final rule entitled &quot;Excess Spoil, Coal Mine Waste, and Buffers for Perennial and Intermittent Streams&quot; (dated December 12, 2008).</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-07-31T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-11-20T17:37:03Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-07-31</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-07-31T21:13:51Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:26:26Z</updateDate>
    <amendments />
    <title>Domestic Energy and Jobs Act</title>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative remedies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Advisory bodies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Air quality</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Alabama</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Alaska</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Alliances</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Alternative and renewable resources</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Arctic and polar regions</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Atlantic Coast (U.S.)</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Atmospheric science and weather</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Canada</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Climate change and greenhouse gases</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Coal</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Competitiveness, trade promotion, trade deficits</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of the Interior</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Economic performance and conditions</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Education programs funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Energy prices</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Energy research</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Energy revenues and royalties</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Energy storage, supplies, demand</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Environmental assessment, monitoring, research</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Environmental regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Gulf of Mexico</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Higher education</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>International organizations and cooperation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Internet and video services</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Judicial review and appeals</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Lakes and rivers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Land use and conservation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Licensing and registrations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Louisiana</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Marine and coastal resources, fisheries</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Military operations and strategy</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Military readiness</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Mining</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Mississippi</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Motor fuels</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Nebraska</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Oil and gas</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Pipelines</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Property rights</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Public Lands and Natural Resources</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Research and development</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Solid waste and recycling</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>South Dakota</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>State and local finance</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Strategic materials and reserves</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Texas</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Unemployment</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Virginia</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water quality</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Energy</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2013-07-31</actionDate>
    </latestAction>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <createDate>2013-08-02T05:52:42Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <laws />
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2013-09-10</actionDate>
          <text>Placed on the Union Calendar, Calendar No. 148.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>BLM Live Internet Auctions Act</latestTitle>
        <number>555</number>
      </item>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2013-04-11</actionDate>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Energy and Mineral Resources.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Advancing Offshore Wind Production Act</latestTitle>
        <number>1398</number>
      </item>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2013-09-10</actionDate>
          <text>Placed on the Union Calendar, Calendar No. 144.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>National Petroleum Reserve Alaska Access Act</latestTitle>
        <number>1964</number>
      </item>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2013-12-09</actionDate>
          <text>Read the second time. Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 254.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Federal Lands Jobs and Energy Security Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <number>1965</number>
      </item>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2013-07-26</actionDate>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Energy and Power.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Gas Accessibility and Stabilization Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <number>2823</number>
      </item>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2013-07-18</actionDate>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Environment and Public Works.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>S</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Gas Accessibility and Stabilization Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <number>1319</number>
      </item>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-01-28</actionDate>
          <text>Committee on Energy and Natural Resources. Hearings held. Hearings printed: S.Hrg. 113-192.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>S</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Critical Minerals Policy Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <number>1600</number>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <actions>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-07-31</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <actionDate>2013-07-31</actionDate>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <links />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <billNumber>1401</billNumber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <state>AK</state>
        <bioguideId>M001153</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1694</lisID>
          <bioguideId>M001153</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8234</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Murkowski, Lisa [R-AK]</fullName>
        <firstName>Lisa</firstName>
        <lastName>Murkowski</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>AR</state>
        <bioguideId>B001236</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1687</lisID>
          <bioguideId>B001236</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8247</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Boozman, John [R-AR]</fullName>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <lastName>Boozman</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>MS</state>
        <bioguideId>C000567</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>213</lisID>
          <gpoId>8292</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>C000567</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Cochran, Thad [R-MS]</fullName>
        <firstName>Thad</firstName>
        <lastName>Cochran</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>LA</state>
        <bioguideId>V000127</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8267</gpoId>
          <lisID>1609</lisID>
          <bioguideId>V000127</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Vitter, David [R-LA]</fullName>
        <firstName>David</firstName>
        <lastName>Vitter</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>ID</state>
        <bioguideId>C000880</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8289</gpoId>
          <lisID>250</lisID>
          <bioguideId>C000880</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Crapo, Mike [R-ID]</fullName>
        <firstName>MICHAEL</firstName>
        <lastName>CRAPO</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName>D.</middleName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>MO</state>
        <bioguideId>B000575</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1464</lisID>
          <gpoId>8313</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>B000575</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Blunt, Roy [R-MO]</fullName>
        <firstName>Roy</firstName>
        <lastName>Blunt</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>WV</state>
        <bioguideId>M001183</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1983</lisID>
          <gpoId>8256</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>M001183</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>D</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Manchin, Joe, III [D-WV]</fullName>
        <firstName>Joe</firstName>
        <lastName>Manchin</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>MS</state>
        <bioguideId>W000437</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>W000437</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8263</gpoId>
          <lisID>1226</lisID>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Wicker, Roger F. [R-MS]</fullName>
        <firstName>ROGER</firstName>
        <lastName>WICKER</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName>F.</middleName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>KS</state>
        <bioguideId>R000307</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>968</lisID>
          <gpoId>8275</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>R000307</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Roberts, Pat [R-KS]</fullName>
        <firstName>PAT</firstName>
        <lastName>ROBERTS</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>GA</state>
        <bioguideId>C000286</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>188</lisID>
          <bioguideId>C000286</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8284</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Chambliss, Saxby [R-GA]</fullName>
        <firstName>SAXBY</firstName>
        <lastName>CHAMBLISS</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
      <item>
        <state>NV</state>
        <bioguideId>H001041</bioguideId>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-03-05</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1863</lisID>
          <bioguideId>H001041</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8060</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Heller, Dean [R-NV]</fullName>
        <firstName>Dean</firstName>
        <lastName>Heller</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <middleName />
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <notes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Energy</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <title>Advancing Offshore Wind Production Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>National Petroleum Reserve Alaska Access Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Providing Leasing Certainty for American Energy Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Gasoline Regulations Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>BLM Live Internet Auctions Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Streamlining Permitting of American Energy Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Planning for American Energy Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Domestic Energy and Jobs Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>A bill to provide for the development of a plan to increase oil and gas exploration, development, and production under oil and gas leases of Federal land, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Domestic Energy and Jobs Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <party>R</party>
        <middleName />
        <bioguideId>H001061</bioguideId>
        <state>ND</state>
        <byRequestType />
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>2079</lisID>
          <gpoId>8331</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>H001061</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <fullName>Sen. Hoeven, John [R-ND]</fullName>
        <lastName>Hoeven</lastName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

