<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <introducedDate>2013-06-27</introducedDate>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDate>2013-06-27</actionDate>
          <updateDate>2013-06-27T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-07-31T14:41:26Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Douglas County Conservation Act of 2013 - Designates specified federal land managed by the Bureau of Land Management (BLM), to be known as the Burbank Canyons Wilderness, as a component of the National Wilderness Preservation System. </p> <p>Releases BLM land in any part of the Burbank Canyon Wilderness not designated as wilderness by this Act from further study for designation as wilderness. </p> <p>Transfers all interest of the United States in certain land which shall be held in trust for the Washoe Tribe of Nevada and California, and which shall become part of the Tribe's reservation.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary of Agriculture (USDA) to implement a cooperative management agreement for the land identified as the Cooperative Management Area in order to: (1) preserve cultural resources, (2) ensure regular access by members of the Tribe and the community across National Forest System land for cultural and religious purposes, and (3) protect recreational uses. </p> <p>Requires the Secretary concerned to convey certain Forest Service land (Lake Tahoe-Nevada State Park) to the state of Nevada, to be used for the conservation of wildlife or natural resources or for a public park. (Defines &quot;Secretary concerned&quot; as the Secretary of Agriculture. acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, for National Forest System lands, and the Secretary of the Interior for land managed by BLM.)</p> <p>Directs the Secretary of Agriculture to make publicly available a prospectus to solicit one or more concessionaires for the lands identified as the Round Hill Pines Resort and Zephyr Shoals. </p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, to transfer from the Forest Service to Nevada, Douglas County (the county), or the applicable unit of local government, certain lands or interests which are unsuitable for Forest Service administration or necessary for a public purpose. </p> <p>Authorizes the Secretary concerned to convey or lease specified lands to the county to be managed for flood control and management, water resource infrastructure, recreation and public purposes, or forest service recreation. </p> <p>Directs the Secretary concerned to conduct one or more sales of specified BLM and county lands to qualified bidders. </p> <p>Amends the Southern Nevada Public Land Management Act of 1998 to specify the use of funds for federal land in Douglas County. </p>]]></text>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-06-27T22:48:20Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:25:49Z</updateDate>
    <amendments />
    <title>Douglas County Conservation Act of 2013</title>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Floods and storm protection</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Forests, forestry, trees</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Indian lands and resources rights</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Land transfers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Land use and conservation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Nevada</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Outdoor recreation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Parks, recreation areas, trails</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water use and supply</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Watersheds</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Wilderness and natural areas, wildlife refuges, wild rivers, habitats</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Wildlife conservation and habitat protection</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Public Lands and Natural Resources</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2013-06-27</actionDate>
    </latestAction>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <createDate>2013-06-28T07:01:14Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <laws />
    <relatedBills />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-06-27</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <committee />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2013-06-27</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <billNumber>1263</billNumber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <middleName>M.</middleName>
        <state>NV</state>
        <firstName>HARRY</firstName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>R000146</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Reid, Harry [D-NV]</fullName>
        <lastName>REID</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-06-27</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>R000146</bioguideId>
          <lisID>952</lisID>
          <gpoId>8271</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <notes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Public Lands and Natural Resources</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <title>Douglas County Conservation Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>A bill to establish a wilderness area, promote conservation, improve public land, and provide for sensible development in Douglas County, Nevada, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Douglas County Conservation Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <party>R</party>
        <middleName />
        <bioguideId>H001041</bioguideId>
        <state>NV</state>
        <byRequestType />
        <firstName>Dean</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1863</lisID>
          <bioguideId>H001041</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8060</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <fullName>Sen. Heller, Dean [R-NV]</fullName>
        <lastName>Heller</lastName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

