<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <relatedBills />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:28:55Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-02-24T20:48:43Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <subcommittees>
            <item>
              <activities>
                <item>
                  <date>2014-02-27T22:10:44Z</date>
                  <name>Hearings by</name>
                </item>
              </activities>
              <systemCode>sseg07</systemCode>
              <name>Water and Power Subcommittee</name>
            </item>
          </subcommittees>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Schatz, Brian [D-HI]</fullName>
        <middleName />
        <bioguideId>S001194</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>2173</lisID>
          <bioguideId>S001194</bioguideId>
          <gpoId />
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <lastName>Schatz</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>HI</state>
        <firstName>Brian</firstName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Water Resources Development</name>
    </policyArea>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2014-02-27</actionDate>
      <text>Committee on Energy and Natural Resources Senate Subcommittee on Water and Power. Hearings held. With printed Hearing: S.Hrg. 113-284.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors />
    <billNumber>2034</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Reclamation Title Transfer Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to authorize the Secretary of the Interior to establish a program to facilitate the transfer to non-Federal ownership of appropriate reclamation projects or facilities, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Reclamation Title Transfer Act of 2014</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <createDate>2014-02-25T07:08:05Z</createDate>
    <notes />
    <title>Reclamation Title Transfer Act of 2014</title>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Dams and canals</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Environmental assessment, monitoring, research</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government buildings, facilities, and property</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Land transfers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Land use and conservation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water use and supply</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Water Resources Development</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <updateDate>2014-02-24T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Reclamation Title Transfer Act of 2014 - Authorizes the Commissioner of the Bureau of Reclamation to establish a program that: (1) identifies and analyzes the potential for public benefits from the transfer of eligible facilities out of federal ownership, and (2) facilitates the transfer of such facilities to qualifying entities to promote more efficient management of water and water-related facilities.</p> <p>Defines: (1) "eligible facilities" as reclamation projects or facilities (including dams and appurtenant works, infrastructure, recreational facilities, buildings, distribution and drainage works, and associated land or interests in land or water) for which the United States holds title and that meet the criteria for potential transfer established by this Act; and (2) "qualifying entity" as a state, local government, Indian tribe, municipal or quasi-municipal corporation, or other entity (such as a water district) that has the capacity to continue to manage the conveyed property for the same purposes that the property has been managed under the reclamation laws.</p> <p>Authorizes the Commissioner to convey an eligible facility to a qualifying entity without further authorization from Congress. Grants a qualifying entity that is operating an eligible facility at the time conveyance is being considered the right of first refusal. </p> <p>Authorizes the Commissioner to reserve an easement over a conveyed property if necessary for the management of any interests retained by the federal government. Directs the Commissioner to retain any mineral interests associated with a conveyed property.</p> <p>Requires the Commissioner to: (1) establish criteria for determining whether facilities are eligible for conveyance under this Act, including that the qualifying entity agrees to use the eligible facility for substantially the same purposes the facility is being used for at the time the transfer is being evaluated and that such a conveyance is in the financial interest of the United States; and (2) make information on how the determinations are made publicly available. </p> <p>Terminates the Secretary's authority to carry out such conveyances 15 years after this Act's enactment.</p>]]></text>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDate>2014-02-24</actionDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-05-14T18:42:59Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <introducedDate>2014-02-24</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <committeeReports />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-02-27</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sseg07</systemCode>
          <name>Water and Power Subcommittee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Committee on Energy and Natural Resources Senate Subcommittee on Water and Power. Hearings held. With printed Hearing: S.Hrg. 113-284.</text>
        <type>Committee</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-02-24</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <committee />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2014-02-24</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>3</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
        <hearingsHeld>1</hearingsHeld>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <recordedVotes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

