<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <createDate>2014-07-09T05:03:41Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>NV</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-07-08</sponsorshipDate>
        <bioguideId>R000146</bioguideId>
        <firstName>HARRY</firstName>
        <middleName>M.</middleName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <fullName>Sen. Reid, Harry [D-NV]</fullName>
        <party>D</party>
        <lastName>REID</lastName>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8271</gpoId>
          <lisID>952</lisID>
          <bioguideId>R000146</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <title>Nevada Mining Townsite Conveyance Act</title>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-07-08</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <actionDate>2014-07-08</actionDate>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <amendments />
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:31:17Z</updateDate>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Public Lands and Natural Resources</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Land transfers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Mining</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Nevada</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <notes />
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
      <actionDate>2014-07-08</actionDate>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>H001041</bioguideId>
        <state>NV</state>
        <fullName>Sen. Heller, Dean [R-NV]</fullName>
        <firstName>Dean</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <lastName>Heller</lastName>
        <middleName />
        <byRequestType />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1863</lisID>
          <bioguideId>H001041</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8060</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <relatedBills />
    <laws />
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-07-08T15:26:02Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Nevada Mining Townsite Conveyance Act - Directs the Secretary of the Interior, acting through the Bureau of Land Management (BLM), to implement an expedited program to examine and determine the validity of each unpatented mining claim (including each claim for which a patent application has been filed) within specified mining townsites (federally owned real property in the Gold Point, Ione, Gold Hill, and Virginia City townsites within Esmeralda, Nye, and Storey, Counties, Nevada, on which improvements were constructed based on the belief that: (1) the property had been or would be acquired from the federal government by the entity that operated the mine, or (2) the individual or entity that made the improvement had a valid claim for acquiring the property from the federal government).</p> <p>Directs the Secretary of the Interior, after completing the validity review, and subject to the county's agreement, to convey to the appropriate county, without consideration, all right, title, and interest of the United States in and to any such mining townsites (including improvements) which are not subject to valid mining claims. Requires the Secretary to reserve the mineral rights in each parcel of land subject to a valid mining claim, but convey, without consideration, the remaining U.S. right, title, and interest.</p> <p>Requires the county receiving such a site, if one or more individuals (occupants, for instance) prove a valid interest under Nevada law, to reconvey the property to such individual or individuals. </p> <p>Withdraws the mining townsites from: (1) all forms of entry, appropriation, or disposal under the public land laws; (2) location, entry, and patent under the mining laws; and (3) disposition under all laws pertaining to mineral and geothermal leasing or mineral materials.</p> <p>Requires withdrawal and conveyance to the owner of the surface rights of any mining claim determined valid which is abandoned, invalidated, or otherwise returned to the BLM.</p> <p>Expresses the sense of Congress that the examination of certain unpatented mining claims and the conveyances should be completed not later than 18 months after enactment of this Act.</p> <p><br> </p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2014-07-08T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-09-30T21:34:00Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2014-07-08</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <recordedVotes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Public Lands and Natural Resources</name>
    </policyArea>
    <introducedDate>2014-07-08</introducedDate>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <billNumber>2566</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Nevada Mining Townsite Conveyance Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to provide for the conveyance of certain public land in and around historic mining townsites located in the State of Nevada, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Nevada Mining Townsite Conveyance Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

