<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <introducedDate>2013-12-12</introducedDate>
    <committeeReports />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <cosponsors />
    <recordedVotes />
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2013-12-12</actionDate>
    </latestAction>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Border and Maritime Security.</text>
          <actionDate>2014-01-02</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>Emergency Port of Entry Personnel and Infrastructure Funding Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Identical bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <number>3753</number>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:28:01Z</updateDate>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Foreign Trade and International Finance</name>
    </policyArea>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-12-12</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <committee />
        <actionDate>2013-12-12</actionDate>
        <links />
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <amendments />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-03-14T16:07:50Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Emergency Port of Entry Personnel and Infrastructure Funding Act of 2013 - Directs the Secretary of Homeland Security (DHS) to hire, train, and assign to duty by September 30, 2019, an additional: (1) 5,000 full-time U.S. Customs and Border Protection (CBP) officers to serve on all inspection lanes and enforcement teams at U.S. land ports of entry on the northern and southern borders of the United States; and (2) 350 full-time support staff for all U.S. ports of entry.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary to report to specified congressional committees on: (1) DHS plans for ensuring the placement of sufficient CBP officers and infrastructure for outbound inspections at southern border land ports of entry; and (2) each relevant department's plans for ensuring the placement of sufficient CBP agriculture specialists, Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service entomologist identifier specialists, and Food and Drug Administration (FDA) consumer safety officers at such ports of entry.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to: (1) ensure that each CBP officer is equipped with a secure two-way communication and satellite-enabled device that allows such officers to communicate between ports of entry and inspection stations and with law enforcement; and (2) establish a program for awarding grants for the purchase of identification and detection equipment and mobile, hand-held, two-way communication devices for state and local law enforcement officers serving on the southern border.</p> <p>Authorizes the Commissioner of CBP to aid in the enforcement of federal customs, immigration, and agriculture laws by: (1) designing, constructing, and modifying U.S. ports of entry, living quarters for personnel, technology and equipment, and other structures and facilities; (2) acquiring land deemed necessary to carry out the Commissioner's duties; and (3) constructing additional ports of entry along the borders. </p> <p> Authorizes the Administrator, for purposes of facilitating the construction, alteration, operation, or maintenance of a new or existing facility or other infrastructure at a port of entry, to: (1) enter into a cost-sharing or reimbursement agreement with the General Services Administration (GSA), or (2) provide GSA with donations of real or person property or nonpersonal services.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to: (1) develop a strategic plan for standardized collection of vehicle wait times at land ports of entry, (2) develop a standardized model for the allocation of CBP officers and support staff at land ports of entry, and (3) identify and adopt new outcome-based performance measures that support the trade facilitation goals of CBP.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary to report to specified congressional committees annually on: (1) DHS's implementation plan for the staff enhancements, (2) the number of additional personnel assigned to duty at land ports of entry, (3) the methodology used to determine the distribution of additional personnel to address northbound and southbound cross-border inspections, (4) the strategic plan, (5) the CBP officer allocation model, and (6) the new outcome-based performance measures.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-12-12T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-12-12</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Foreign Trade and International Finance</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Agricultural trade</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Animal and plant health</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Appropriations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Border security and unlawful immigration</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Customs enforcement</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Homeland Security</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Executive agency funding and structure</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government employee pay, benefits, personnel management</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Law enforcement officers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Performance measurement</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <title>Emergency Port of Entry Personnel and Infrastructure Funding Act of 2013</title>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <lastName>Cornyn</lastName>
        <bioguideId>C001056</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Cornyn, John [R-TX]</fullName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1692</lisID>
          <gpoId>8295</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>C001056</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>R</party>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <middleName />
        <state>TX</state>
        <byRequestType />
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <laws />
    <notes />
    <createDate>2013-12-13T08:01:22Z</createDate>
    <billNumber>1812</billNumber>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-12-12T20:05:47Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <subcommittees />
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Emergency Port of Entry Personnel and Infrastructure Funding Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to provide emergency funding for port of entry personnel and infrastructure.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Emergency Port of Entry Personnel and Infrastructure Funding Act of 2013</title>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

