<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE resolution PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/res.dtd//EN" "res.dtd">
<resolution dms-id="H40AF6B9B70994D6CA730D0D19D3E8ECF" public-private="public" resolution-stage="Introduced-in-House" resolution-type="house-concurrent" star-print="no-star-print" key="H"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">IV</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">112th CONGRESS</congress> 
<session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. CON. RES. 4</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20110105">January 5, 2011</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</sponsor> submitted the following concurrent resolution; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>CONCURRENT RESOLUTION</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">Expressing the sense of Congress that the Supreme Court misinterpreted the First Amendment to the Constitution in the case of Buckley v. Valeo.</official-title> 
</form> 
<resolution-body style="traditional" id="H65B07984F3434D80AD55779656E3A09A"> 
<section display-inline="yes-display-inline" section-type="undesignated-section" id="H4A5845ADE84F4839BB1E4F11E5CE44E5"><text>That it is the sense of Congress that the Supreme Court misinterpreted the First Amendment to the Constitution in its decision in the 1976 case of Buckley v. Valeo because—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF686D178727C4B13938C321104F5108C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the decision failed to recognize that the unlimited spending of large amounts of money on elections has a corrosive effect on the electoral process not simply because of direct transactions between those who give large amounts of money and candidates and elected officials but because the presence of unlimited amounts of money corrupts the process on a more fundamental level; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA4C3F24123C3421797C6341D592CA411"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the decision failed to recognize other legitimate state interests which justify limiting money in campaigns, including the need to preserve the integrity of our republican form of government, restore public confidence in government, and ensure all citizens a more equal opportunity to participate in the political process.</text></paragraph></section> 
</resolution-body> 
</resolution> 
