<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <createDate>2013-09-20T07:01:07Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>B001230</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>B001230</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8215</gpoId>
          <lisID>1558</lisID>
        </identifiers>
        <middleName />
        <fullName>Sen. Baldwin, Tammy [D-WI]</fullName>
        <firstName>TAMMY</firstName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-06-24</sponsorshipDate>
        <lastName>BALDWIN</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <party>D</party>
        <state>WI</state>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <title>Freedom and Mobility in Consumer Banking Act</title>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-09-19</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssbk00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <committee />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2013-09-19</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <links />
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <amendments />
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:26:58Z</updateDate>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Finance and Financial Sector</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Bank accounts, deposits, capital</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Consumer Financial Protection Bureau</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Consumer affairs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Consumer credit</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <notes />
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs.</text>
      <actionDate>2013-09-19</actionDate>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>H000206</bioguideId>
        <state>IA</state>
        <fullName>Sen. Harkin, Tom [D-IA]</fullName>
        <firstName>THOMAS</firstName>
        <party>D</party>
        <lastName>HARKIN</lastName>
        <middleName>RICHARD</middleName>
        <byRequestType />
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8317</gpoId>
          <lisID>501</lisID>
          <bioguideId>H000206</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <type>HR</type>
        <number>3137</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Referred to the House Committee on Financial Services.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-09-19</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Identical bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Freedom and Mobility in Consumer Banking Act</latestTitle>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <laws />
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-09-19T20:27:40Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <name>Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee</name>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>ssbk00</systemCode>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <updateDate>2013-09-19T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Freedom and Mobility in Consumer Banking Act - Amends the Truth in Savings Act to prohibit depository institutions from: (1) prohibiting a consumer from closing a covered account (a checking, savings, or any other account that the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection [CFPB] may include), regardless of whether the balance is positive, zero, or negative; (2) charging any fee to close such account; or (3) reopening such an account to apply subsequent debits after a consumer has requested the account to be closed, unless the consumer requests that the account be reopened.</p> <p>Requires depository institutions to provide consumers with a description of the policies and procedures in place to close such accounts at the time the account is opened, upon request, and on the websites of such institutions.</p> <p>Directs the CFPB to prescribe regulations relating to the closure of such accounts, including: (1) allowing consumers to receive available funds from a closed account in the form of a cashier's check, electronic funds transfer, or any other means offered by the institution or determined appropriate by the CFPB; (2) requiring depository institutions to provide consumers with certain information regarding any preauthorized transactions or direct deposits associated with an account before it is closed; (3) prohibiting a depository institution from reporting adverse information regarding such account to any consumer reporting agency if, at the time the account is closed, the account has a negative balance resulting solely from any fee assessed by the depository institution; and (4) establishing the terms under which a depository institution may report to a consumer reporting agency that an account had a negative closing balance, provided that the institution notifies the consumer and provides a reasonable period for repayment of the balance. </p> <p>Directs the Comptroller General (GAO) to report to Congress and the CFPB regarding additional barriers that could limit the ability of a consumer to close a covered account. Requires the CFPB, after receiving such report, to determine whether regulations should be issued to remove such barriers.</p>]]></text>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDate>2013-09-19</actionDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-10-17T20:28:53Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <recordedVotes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Finance and Financial Sector</name>
    </policyArea>
    <introducedDate>2013-09-19</introducedDate>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <billNumber>1534</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <title>Freedom and Mobility in Consumer Banking Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>A bill to provide a framework establishing the rights, liabilities, and responsibilities of participants in closing procedures for certain types of consumer deposit accounts, to protect individual consumer rights, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Freedom and Mobility in Consumer Banking Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

