<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <introducedDate>2013-05-14</introducedDate>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Consumer Mortgage Choice Act - Amends the Truth in Lending Act with respect to requirements for disclosure to a consumer of points and fees information about a consumer credit transaction, secured by the consumer's principal dwelling, but which is not a residential mortgage transaction, a reverse mortgage transaction, or a transaction under an open end credit plan, when the total points and fees the consumer must pay at or before closing will exceed 8% percent of the total loan amount or $400, whichever is greater. (Such consumer credit transactions might include an equity credit line to which consumer purchases or leases may be charged.)</p> <p>Excludes from the computation of such points and fees: (1) any compensation paid by a mortgage originator or a creditor to an individual person employed by the mortgage originator or creditor, and (2) any escrow for future payment of insurance.</p> <p>Modifies the inclusion in the computation of points and fees of all compensation paid to mortgage brokers. Specifies instead all compensation paid directly by a consumer to a mortgage originator, including a mortgage originator that is also the creditor in a table-funded transaction, but not including compensation paid by a mortgage originator or a creditor to an individual employed by the mortgage originator or creditor.</p> <p>Modifies the criteria for exclusion from the computation of points and fees of certain reasonable charges elsewhere exempted from the computation of the finance charge in extensions of credit secured by an interest in real property. Excludes from points and fees any such reasonable charges even though a creditor receives compensation, but only in so far as the creditor or its affiliate retains the compensation as a result of their participation in an affiliated business arrangement. </p> <p>(An "affiliated business arrangement" is one in which: (1) a person who is in a position to refer business incident to or a part of a real estate settlement service involving a federally related mortgage loan, or an associate of such person, has either an affiliate relationship with or a direct or beneficial ownership interest of more than 1% in a provider of settlement services; and (2) either of such persons directly or indirectly refers such business to that provider or affirmatively influences the provider's selection.)</p> <p>Revises the additional requirement that such a reasonable charge be paid to a third party unaffiliated with the creditor. Requires the charge to be: (1) a bona fide third party charge not retained by the mortgage originator, creditor, or an affiliate; or (2) a fee or premium for title examination, title insurance, or similar purposes. </p> <p>Modifies the conditions under which federal departments and agencies may exempt refinancings under a streamlined refinancing from an income verification requirement that, at the time a refinancing is consummated, the consumer has a reasonable ability to repay the loan and all applicable taxes, insurance, and assessments. Repeals the exception for bona fide third party charges not retained by the mortgage originator, creditor, or an affiliate from the requirement that total points and fees not exceed 3% of the total new loan amount. (Thus subjects such charges to the same 3% ceiling.)</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-05-14T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2013-11-25T21:30:33Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-05-14</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>ssbk00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2013-05-14T21:08:13Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee</name>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:24:22Z</updateDate>
    <amendments />
    <title>Consumer Mortgage Choice Act</title>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Housing and Community Development</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Housing finance and home ownership</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>User charges and fees</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs.</text>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2013-05-14</actionDate>
    </latestAction>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <createDate>2013-05-15T07:02:14Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <laws />
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <number>1077</number>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2013-03-12</actionDate>
          <text>Referred to the House Committee on Financial Services.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>Consumer Mortgage Choice Act</latestTitle>
      </item>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <number>1577</number>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-09-16</actionDate>
          <text>Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs. Hearings held.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>Mortgage Choice Act of 2013</latestTitle>
      </item>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <number>2767</number>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2013-07-24</actionDate>
          <text>Ordered to be Reported (Amended) by the Yeas and Nays: 30 - 27.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>Protecting American Taxpayers and Homeowners Act of 2013</latestTitle>
      </item>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <number>3211</number>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-06-10</actionDate>
          <text>Received in the Senate.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>Mortgage Choice Act of 2013</latestTitle>
      </item>
      <item>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <number>5461</number>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-09-17</actionDate>
          <text>Received in the Senate and Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <latestTitle>To clarify the application of certain leverage and risk-based requirements under the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act, to improve upon the definitions provided for points and fees in connection with a mortgage transaction, and for other purposes.</latestTitle>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <actions>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-05-14</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssbk00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <actionDate>2013-05-14</actionDate>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <links />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <billNumber>949</billNumber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <middleName />
        <state>NE</state>
        <firstName>Mike</firstName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>J000291</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Johanns, Mike [R-NE]</fullName>
        <lastName>Johanns</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-05-14</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1899</lisID>
          <bioguideId>J000291</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8325</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
      </item>
      <item>
        <middleName />
        <state>GA</state>
        <firstName>Johnny</firstName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>I000055</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Isakson, Johnny [R-GA]</fullName>
        <lastName>Isakson</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-11-13</sponsorshipDate>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1608</lisID>
          <gpoId>8323</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>I000055</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <notes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Housing and Community Development</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Consumer Mortgage Choice Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to amend the Truth in Lending Act to improve upon the definitions provided for points and fees in connection with a mortgage transaction.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Consumer Mortgage Choice Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <party>D</party>
        <middleName />
        <bioguideId>M001183</bioguideId>
        <state>WV</state>
        <byRequestType />
        <firstName>Joe</firstName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1983</lisID>
          <gpoId>8256</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>M001183</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <fullName>Sen. Manchin, Joe, III [D-WV]</fullName>
        <lastName>Manchin</lastName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

