<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <relatedBills />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:28:45Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2014-02-06T20:43:53Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Baucus, Max [D-MT]</fullName>
        <middleName>SIEBEN</middleName>
        <bioguideId>B000243</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>B000243</bioguideId>
          <lisID>66</lisID>
          <gpoId>8298</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <lastName>BAUCUS</lastName>
        <party>D</party>
        <state>MT</state>
        <firstName>MAX</firstName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Water Resources Development</name>
    </policyArea>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2014-02-06</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <lastName>Walsh</lastName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <fullName>Sen. Walsh, John E. [D-MT]</fullName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>2198</lisID>
          <gpoId />
          <bioguideId>W000818</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <party>D</party>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-06-12</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName>E.</middleName>
        <bioguideId>W000818</bioguideId>
        <state>MT</state>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <billNumber>1997</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Dry-Redwater Regional Water Authority System Act of 2014</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to authorize the Dry-Redwater Regional Water Authority System.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Dry-Redwater Regional Water Authority System Act of 2014</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <createDate>2014-02-07T07:02:44Z</createDate>
    <notes />
    <title>Dry-Redwater Regional Water Authority System Act of 2014</title>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Water Resources Development</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Electric power generation and transmission</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Missouri River</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Montana</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>North Dakota</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water resources funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water use and supply</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDate>2014-02-06</actionDate>
          <updateDate>2014-02-06T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-03-26T20:10:52Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Dry-Redwater Regional Water Authority System Act of 2014 - Authorizes the Secretary of the Interior to carry out the project entitled the &quot;Dry-Redwater Regional Water Authority System&quot; in accordance with the plans described in the &quot;Dry-Redwater Regional Water System Feasibility Study&quot; if the Secretary determines that the project is feasible.</p> <p>Directs the Secretary to enter into a cooperative agreement to provide federal assistance for the planning, design, and construction of the System for specified counties in Montana and North Dakota. </p> <p>Limits the federal share of planning, design, and construction of the System to 75% of the total cost, or such other lesser amount as may be determined by the Commissioner of Reclamation in a feasibility report. Delineates the components of System facilities for which federal funds may be expended. Prohibits federal funds from being used for the System's operation, maintenance, or replacement.</p> <p>Directs the Administrator of the Western Area Power Administration to make available to the System a quantity of power required, up to one and a half megawatt capacity, to meet the System's pumping and incidental operation requirements between May 1 and October 31 of each year from the water intake facilities and through all pumping stations, water treatment facilities, reservoirs, storage tanks, and pipelines up to the point of delivery of water by the water supply system to all storage reservoirs and tanks and each entity that distributes water at retail to individual users. Makes the System eligible to receive such power only if it operates on a nonprofit basis and is constructed pursuant to the cooperative agreement. Sets forth provisions regarding the purchase of additional power, the Authority's responsibility for power charges and non-federal delivery costs, and the System's responsibility for non-federal transmission and distribution system delivery and service arrangements and for funding any transmission upgrades required to the integrated system necessary to deliver power to the System. </p>]]></text>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <introducedDate>2014-02-06</introducedDate>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <committeeReports />
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-02-06</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sseg00</systemCode>
          <name>Energy and Natural Resources Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-02-06</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <recordedVotes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

