<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <title>CURB Act</title>
    <createDate>2013-11-20T07:01:06Z</createDate>
    <billNumber>1730</billNumber>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>C001035</bioguideId>
        <middleName>MARGARET</middleName>
        <fullName>Sen. Collins, Susan M. [R-ME]</fullName>
        <firstName>SUSAN</firstName>
        <byRequestType />
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>C001035</bioguideId>
          <lisID>1541</lisID>
          <gpoId>8291</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>COLLINS</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <state>ME</state>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <cosponsors />
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <number>2747</number>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
            <type>Related bill</type>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Small Business Regulatory Sunset Act of 2014</latestTitle>
        <type>S</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
          <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced for portions of this bill</titleType>
        <title>Regulatory Flexibility Improvement Act of 2013</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>CURB Act</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Clearing Unnecessary Regulatory Burdens Act of 2013</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to reform the regulatory process to ensure that small businesses are free to compete and to create jobs, to clear unnecessary regulatory burdens, and for other purposes.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>CURB Act</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <introducedDate>2013-11-19</introducedDate>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
      <actionDate>2013-11-19</actionDate>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <amendments />
    <committeeReports />
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Government Operations and Politics</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Business records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Economic performance and conditions</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Executive agency funding and structure</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Federal officials</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Judicial review and appeals</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Public participation and lobbying</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Small Business Administration</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Small business</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Tax administration and collection, taxpayers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Unemployment</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <laws />
    <notes />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-11-19</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>B00100</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <committee />
        <actionDate>2013-11-19</actionDate>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <links>
          <link>
            <name>S8192-8193</name>
            <url>https://www.congress.gov/congressional-record/volume-159/senate-section/page/S8192-8193</url>
          </link>
        </links>
        <text>Sponsor introductory remarks on measure. (CR S8192-8193)</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <committee />
        <actionDate>2013-11-19</actionDate>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <links />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <placeholderTextForB>1</placeholderTextForB>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <recordedVotes />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Clearing Unnecessary Regulatory Burdens Act of 2013 or the CURB Act - Requires each federal agency to: (1) report to the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs of the Office of Management and Budget (OMB) on the costs and benefits of each significant regulatory action and of identified alternatives; (2) develop or have written procedures for the approval of significant guidance documents; (3) maintain on its website a list of such documents in effect; (4) establish and advertise on its website a means for the public to electronically submit comments on such documents and a request for issuance, reconsideration, modification, or rescission of such documents; and (5) publish a notice in the Federal Register announcing that a draft of an economically significant guidance document is available, make such document publicly available, invite comment on such draft, and respond to such comments.</p> <p>Defines an "economically significant regulatory action, a &quot;significant guidance document," and a &quot;significant regulatory action&quot; for purposes of this Act as regulatory actions or documents that may have an annual effect on the economy of $100 million or more or that may adversely affect the economy in a material way. </p> <p>Requires agencies to notify the Administrator in emergency situations or when they are obligated by law to act more quickly than normal review procedures allow.</p> <p>Allows a reduction or waiver of civil penalties on small entities for failure to comply with regulatory requirements.</p> <p>Regulatory Flexibility Improvement Act of 2013 - Amends the Regulatory Flexibility Act (RFA) to revise the regulatory process (rulemaking) with respect to small entities.</p> <p>Defines "economic impact," with respect to a proposed or final rule, to mean: (1) the economic effects on small entities directly regulated by the rule, and (2) the reasonably foreseeable economic effects of the rule on small entities resulting from their transactions with other businesses and entities directly regulated by the rule.</p> <p>Expands judicial review of agency rulemaking to permit small entities to: (1) seek judicial review of initial regulatory flexibility analyses, and (2) obtain an injunction of a proposed rule that is noncompliant with RFA requirements. </p> <p>Requires each agency to establish a plan for the periodic review (every nine years) of: (1) its rules that have a significant adverse economic impact on small entities, and (2) any small entity compliance guide required to be published by an agency. Sets forth criteria for review of a rule, including the continued need for the rule, the complexity of the rule, and the impact of the rule on small entities. </p> <p>Extends RFA requirements to significant agency guidance documents.</p> <p>Amends the Small Business Regulatory Enforcement Fairness Act of 1996 to require each agency to review on a periodic basis the civil penalties it imposes on small entities for violations of statutory or regulatory requirements. </p> <p>Imposes certain additional requirements on agencies prior to the issuance of a final rule, including requirements for: (1) publication of an initial regulatory flexibility analysis, (2) a determination of the average cost of a rule for affected small entities and the number of small entities affected or reasonably presumed to be affected, and (3) consultation with the Chief Counsel for Advocacy for the Small Business Administration (SBA) with respect to the accuracy of information relating to the cost and impact of a final rule.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-11-19T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-02-06T20:52:20Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-11-19</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:27:42Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2013-11-19T20:09:56Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <subcommittees />
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Government Operations and Politics</name>
    </policyArea>
    <calendarNumbers />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

