<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2013-07-18</actionDate>
      <text>Introduced in the Senate. Read twice. Ordered Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 143.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <committeeReports />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees />
    </committees>
    <laws />
    <createDate>2013-07-19T07:02:06Z</createDate>
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-07-18</actionDate>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Introduced in the Senate. Read twice. Ordered Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 143.</text>
        <type>Calendars</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2013-07-18</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <placedOnCalendarSection>1</placedOnCalendarSection>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <recordedVotes />
    <amendments />
    <introducedDate>2013-07-18</introducedDate>
    <billNumber>1335</billNumber>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Public Lands and Natural Resources</name>
    </policyArea>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p>Sportsmen's Act - <b>Title I: Recreational Shooting</b> - Requires a federal public land management official, in cooperation with the respective state and fish and wildlife agency, to exercise the authority of the official under law, including regarding land use planning, to facilitate the use of, and access to, federal public land for hunting, recreational fishing, and recreational shooting, except as described in this Act.</p> <p>Requires the heads of federal public land management agencies to exercise their discretion in a manner that supports and facilitates hunting, recreational fishing, and recreational shooting opportunities, to the extent authorized under applicable law.</p> <p>Requires that Bureau of Land Management (BLM) and Forest Service land, excluding land on the Outer Continental Shelf, be open to hunting, recreational fishing, or recreational shooting unless the managing agency acts to close lands to such activity. Permits closures or restrictions on such land for purposes including resource conservation, public safety, energy or mineral production, energy generation or transmission infrastructure, water supply facilities, national security, or compliance with other law.</p> <p>Allows agencies to: (1) lease or permit use of federal public land for recreational shooting ranges, and (2) designate specific land for recreational shooting activities. Excepts from such use or designation land including a component of the National Wilderness Preservation System, land designated as a wilderness study area or administratively classified as wilderness eligible or suitable, and primitive or semiprimitive areas.</p> <p>Requires annual reports on closures of federal public lands to hunting, recreational fishing, or recreational shooting. Sets forth requirements for specified closures or significant restrictions involving 1280 or more contiguous acres of federal public land or water to hunting or recreational fishing or related activities.</p> <p>Instructs federal public land agencies to consult with the advisory councils specified in Executive Orders 12962 (relating to recreational fisheries) and 13443 (relating to the facilitation of hunting heritage and wildlife conservation) in carrying out this Act.</p> <p>Requires the Secretary of the Interior to permit individuals carrying bows and crossbows to traverse the National Park System if the traverse is: (1) for the sole purpose of hunting on adjacent land, and (2) the most direct means of access to such adjacent land.</p> <p>Prohibits the Secretary of the Army from promulgating or enforcing any regulation that prohibits an individual from possessing a firearm at a water resources development project administered by the Chief of Engineers if: (1) the individual is not otherwise prohibited by law from possessing the firearm, and (2) the possession of the firearm is in compliance with the law of the state in which the project is located.</p> <p>Amends the Marine Mammal Protection Act of 1972 to direct the Secretary of the Interior to issue a permit for the importation of any polar bear part (other than an internal organ) from a polar bear taken in a sport hunt in Canada to any person who submits proof that the polar bear was legally harvested before May 15, 2008 (currently by February 18, 1997), when polar bears were listed as a threatened species by the Department of the Interior.</p> <p>Amends the Pittman-Robertson Wildlife Restoration Act to: (1) authorize a state to pay up to 90% of the costs of acquiring land for, expanding, or constructing a public target range; (2) authorize a state to elect to allocate 10% of a specified amount apportioned to it from the federal aid to wildlife restoration fund for such costs; (3) limit the federal share of such costs under such Act to 90%; and (4) require amounts provided for such costs under such Act to remain available for expenditure and obligation for five fiscal years.</p> <p>Shields the United States from any civil action or claim for money damages for injury to or loss of property, personal injury, or death caused by an activity occurring at a public target range that is funded by the federal government pursuant to such Act or located on federal land, except to the extent provided under the Federal Tort Claims Act with respect to the exercise or performance of a discretionary function.</p> <p>Urges the Chief of the Forest Service and the Director of BLM to cooperate with state and local authorities and other entities to carry out waste removal and other activities on any federal land used as a public target range to encourage its continued use for target practice or marksmanship training.</p> <p><b>Title II: Duck Stamps</b> - Amends the Fish and Wildlife Improvement Act of 1978 to exempt an authorized taking of migratory birds and collection of their eggs by indigenous inhabitants of Alaska from the prohibition on taking under the Migratory Bird Hunting and Conservation Stamp Act.</p> <p>Grants the Secretary of the Interior permanent authority to authorize any state to issue electronic duck stamps. </p> <p>Sets forth state electronic duck stamp application requirements. </p> <p>Allows the Secretary to determine the number of new states permitted per year to participate in the electronic duck stamp program. </p> <p>Instructs the Secretary to require electronic stamp revenue and customer information collected by each state to be transmitted in accordance with a written agreement between the Secretary and the state.</p> <p><b>Title III: Reauthorizations</b> - Amends the Federal Land Transaction Facilitation Act (FLTFA) to reauthorize, until 15 years after this Act's enactment, the program for the completion of appraisals and satisfaction of other legal requirements for the sale or exchange of public land identified for disposal under approved land use plans under the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976. </p> <p>Requires 30% (currently all) of the gross proceeds of the sale or exchange of public land under such Act to be deposited in the Federal Land Disposal Account and 70% of such proceeds to be deposited in the general fund of the Treasury and used for federal budget deficit reduction.</p> <p>Makes the FLTFA inapplicable to land eligible for sale under specified public land laws. </p> <p>Amends the North American Wetlands Conservation Act to extend through FY2017 the authorization of appropriations for allocations to carry out approved wetlands conservation projects.</p> <p><b>Title IV: Miscellaneous</b> - Amends the Toxic Substances Control Act (TSCA) to exclude from the definition of "chemical substance" for purposes of such Act: (1) any component of any pistol, revolver, firearm, shell, or cartridge the sale of which is subject to federal excise tax, including shot, bullets and other projectiles, propellants, and primers; and (2) any sport fishing equipment the sale of which is subject to federal excise tax and sport fishing equipment components. </p> <p>Requires the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Agriculture (USDA), for any film crew of five persons or fewer, to require a permit and assess an annual fee of $200 for commercial filming activities or similar projects on federal land and waterways administered by the Secretary. Makes such a permit valid for such activities or projects that occur in areas designated for public use during public hours on all federal land and waterways administered by the Secretary for a one-year period. Allows an applicable land management agency to deny access to a film crew if: (1) there is a likelihood of resource damage that cannot be mitigated, (2) there would be an unreasonable disruption of the public use and enjoyment of the site, (3) the activity poses public health or safety risks, and (4) the filming includes the use of models or props that are not part of the land's natural or cultural resources or administrative facilities.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2013-07-18T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-07-22T17:05:54Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2013-07-18</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <congress>113</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Alaska</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Alaska Natives and Hawaiians</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Animal protection and human-animal relationships</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Art, artists, authorship</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Birds</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Budget deficits and national debt</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Canada</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Endangered and threatened species</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Firearms and explosives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Forests, forestry, trees</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Hazardous wastes and toxic substances</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Hunting and fishing</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Lakes and rivers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Land transfers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Land use and conservation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Licensing and registrations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Mammals</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Outdoor recreation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Parks, recreation areas, trails</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Solid waste and recycling</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Television and film</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Trade restrictions</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>User charges and fees</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Water use and supply</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Wetlands</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Wilderness and natural areas, wildlife refuges, wild rivers, habitats</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Wildlife conservation and habitat protection</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Public Lands and Natural Resources</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <title>Sportsmen's Act</title>
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:26:08Z</updateDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>Sportsmen's Act</title>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>A bill to protect and enhance opportunities for recreational hunting, fishing, and shooting, and for other purposes.</title>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <title>Sportsmen's Act</title>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <state>AK</state>
        <firstName>Lisa</firstName>
        <byRequestType />
        <bioguideId>M001153</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Murkowski, Lisa [R-AK]</fullName>
        <lastName>Murkowski</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <middleName />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1694</lisID>
          <bioguideId>M001153</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8234</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <calendarNumbers>
      <item>
        <number>0143</number>
        <calendar>Senate Calendar of Business</calendar>
      </item>
    </calendarNumbers>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Permanent Electronic Duck Stamp Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <number>1206</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Became Public Law No: 113-239.</text>
          <actionDate>2014-12-18</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Target Practice and Marksmanship Training Support Act</latestTitle>
        <number>2463</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Placed on the Union Calendar, Calendar No. 178.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-10-22</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Recreational Fishing and Hunting Heritage and Opportunities Act</latestTitle>
        <number>170</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-01-29</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Permanent Electronic Duck Stamp Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <number>738</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Environment and Public Works.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-04-16</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Polar Bear Conservation and Fairness Act of 2013</latestTitle>
        <number>847</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-04-25</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Target Practice and Marksmanship Training Support Act</latestTitle>
        <number>1212</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Environment and Public Works.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-06-20</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
          <item>
            <type>Text similarities</type>
            <identifiedBy>House</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Sportsmen's Heritage And Recreational Enhancement Act</latestTitle>
        <number>3590</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read the second time. Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 305.</text>
          <actionDate>2014-02-10</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>SPORT Act</latestTitle>
        <number>1660</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Environment and Public Works.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-11-06</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Hunting, Fishing, and Recreational Shooting Protection Act</latestTitle>
        <number>1505</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Environment and Public Works.</text>
          <actionDate>2013-09-17</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>S</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>Bipartisan Sportsmen's Act of 2014</latestTitle>
        <number>1996</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read the second time. Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 304.</text>
          <actionDate>2014-02-06</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
      <item>
        <type>HR</type>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <latestTitle>To amend Public Law 106-206 to direct the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Agriculture to require annual permits and assess annual fees for commercial filming activities on Federal land for film crews of 5 persons or fewer.</latestTitle>
        <number>2798</number>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Placed on the Union Calendar, Calendar No. 248.</text>
          <actionDate>2014-01-29</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <firstName>ROB</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Portman, Rob [R-OH]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>P000449</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>924</lisID>
          <gpoId>8266</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>P000449</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>PORTMAN</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>OH</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-23</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Barrasso, John [R-WY]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>B001261</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1881</lisID>
          <gpoId>8300</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>B001261</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Barrasso</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>WY</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-23</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Boozman, John [R-AR]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>B001236</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1687</lisID>
          <bioguideId>B001236</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8247</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Boozman</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>AR</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-23</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>David</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Vitter, David [R-LA]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>V000127</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>V000127</bioguideId>
          <lisID>1609</lisID>
          <gpoId>8267</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Vitter</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>LA</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-30</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>RICHARD</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Burr, Richard [R-NC]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>B001135</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>B001135</bioguideId>
          <lisID>153</lisID>
          <gpoId>8286</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>BURR</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>NC</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-07-31</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>James</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Risch, James E. [R-ID]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>R000584</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1896</lisID>
          <gpoId>8274</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>R000584</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Risch</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>ID</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-08-01</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName>E.</middleName>
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>JOHN</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Thune, John [R-SD]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>T000250</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1534</lisID>
          <gpoId>8257</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>T000250</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>THUNE</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>SD</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-08-01</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName>R.</middleName>
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Hoeven, John [R-ND]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>H001061</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>2079</lisID>
          <gpoId>8331</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>H001061</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Hoeven</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>ND</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-09-23</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>Dean</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Heller, Dean [R-NV]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>H001041</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1863</lisID>
          <gpoId>8060</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>H001041</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Heller</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>NV</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-10-03</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>MITCH</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. McConnell, Mitch [R-KY]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>M000355</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1395</lisID>
          <bioguideId>M000355</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8254</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>MCCONNELL</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>KY</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2013-11-07</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Cornyn, John [R-TX]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>C001056</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8295</gpoId>
          <lisID>1692</lisID>
          <bioguideId>C001056</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>Cornyn</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>TX</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-01-27</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <firstName>JEFF</firstName>
        <party>R</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Flake, Jeff [R-AZ]</fullName>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>False</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <bioguideId>F000444</bioguideId>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1633</lisID>
          <gpoId>7803</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>F000444</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <lastName>FLAKE</lastName>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <state>AZ</state>
        <sponsorshipDate>2014-06-17</sponsorshipDate>
        <middleName />
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <notes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

